<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Chymical disceptations, or, Discourses upon acid and alkali wherein are examined the object of Mr. Boyle against these principles : together with a reply to a letter of Mr. S. Doctor of Physick &amp; fellow of the colleg of *** : wherein many errors are corrected, touching the nature of these two salts / by Fran. Andre, Dr. in Physick ..., faithfully rendered out of French into English by J.W. ; to which is added, by the translator, a discourse of phlebotomy shewing the absolute evils, together with the accidental benefits thereof, in some cases.</title>
            <title>Entretiéns sur l'acide et sur l'alkali. English</title>
            <author>Saint André, François de, fl. 1677-1725.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1689</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 152 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 111 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A25375</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing A3113A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R30709</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11413725</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 11413725</idno>
            <idno type="VID">47737</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A25375)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 47737)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1453:47)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Chymical disceptations, or, Discourses upon acid and alkali wherein are examined the object of Mr. Boyle against these principles : together with a reply to a letter of Mr. S. Doctor of Physick &amp; fellow of the colleg of *** : wherein many errors are corrected, touching the nature of these two salts / by Fran. Andre, Dr. in Physick ..., faithfully rendered out of French into English by J.W. ; to which is added, by the translator, a discourse of phlebotomy shewing the absolute evils, together with the accidental benefits thereof, in some cases.</title>
                  <title>Entretiéns sur l'acide et sur l'alkali. English</title>
                  <author>Saint André, François de, fl. 1677-1725.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[12], 166, [4], 1, 6-30 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Tho. Dawks and Benj. Allport ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1689.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Imperfect: pages have print show-through and are tightly bound with some loss of print.</note>
                  <note>Translation of author's Entretiéns sur l'acide et sur l'alkali.</note>
                  <note>Pages 6 and 7 are repeated once within the first numbering sequence.</note>
                  <note>"Errores phlebo[to]miæ detecti, or, the errors of phlebotomy discovered ..." has special t.p. and separate paging.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Glasgow University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Chemistry --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Acids.</term>
               <term>Alkalies.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>Greg Schutz</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Rekeyed and resubmitted</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>Louis Goldberg</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>Louis Goldberg</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <group>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="imprimatur">
                  <pb facs="tcp:47737:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:47737:1"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:47737:2"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:47737:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:47737:3"/>
                  <opener>
                     <dateline>
                        <date>Septemb. 26. 1688.</date>
                     </dateline>
                  </opener>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Libellus cui Titulus,</hi> Chymical Diſ. ceptations, or Diſcourſes upon Acid and Alkali, &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>Imprimatur, <hi>Tho. Witherly,</hi> Aeq. aur. Col. Med. Lond. <hi>Praeſes.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <list>
                     <head>Cenſores.</head>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Pe. Barwick</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Joh. Elliot</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Rob. Pitt.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Joh. Bateman</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </div>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:47737:3"/>
                  <p>Chymical Diſceptations:</p>
                  <p>OR, DISCOURSES UPON ACID and ALKALI.</p>
                  <p>Wherein are Examined the OBJECTIONS Of Mr. <hi rend="blackletterType">Boyle</hi> againſt theſe PRINCIPLES.</p>
                  <p>Together with a REPLY to a Letter of Mr. S. Doctor of Physick, &amp; Fellow of the Colledg of ***, wherein many Errors are corrected, touching the Nature of theſe two SALTS.</p>
                  <p>By <hi>Fran. Andre,</hi> Dr. in Phyſick, of the Faculty of <hi>Caën.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Faithfully rendred out of French into Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh By <hi>J. W.</hi> 
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</p>
                  <p>To which is added, by the Tranſlator, a Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe of Phlebotomy, ſhewing the Abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute Evils, together with the Accidental Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefits thereof, in ſome Caſes.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>London,</hi> Printed for <hi>Tho. Dawks,</hi> on Addle Hill in <hi>Carter</hi>-lane, and <hi>Benj. Allport,</hi> at the white Horſe in <hi>Little Britain.</hi> 1689.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="to_the_reader">
                  <pb facs="tcp:47737:4"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:47737:4"/>
                  <head>THE Tranſlator to the READER.</head>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>Kind Reader,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I</hi> Have here preſented Thee with an Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent Treatiſe of a learned French man in an Engliſh Dreſs, and though, perhaps, it be not <hi>a la mode,</hi> and conſequently the leſs acceptable to vulgar Spirits; yet, to the Learned and Impartial Readers, it will ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear a Work of no mall Worth, eſpecially when they ſhall Justly weigh thoſe Solid Reaſons the Author gives in Defence of the <hi>Hypotheſis</hi> of <hi>Acid</hi> and <hi>Alkali,</hi> and the Weakneſs of thoſe <hi>Objections</hi> against it: the first being deduced from Reaſon and Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience, and the last only from over-curi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Suppoſition: The Work pleads ſo ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciently its own Worth, that all Commenda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions
<pb facs="tcp:47737:5"/>come much ſhort of it. 'Tis a Book ſo Uſeful and Neceſſary in Diſpelling thoſe Mists of Ignorance we at preſent generally labour under, that 'tis Pity Our Engliſh Tongue was not honored with it from a more accompliſh'd Pen, long before this; ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it is a Book which more particularly concerns us than any other Nation, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect, That that learned and Ingenious Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon that made thoſe ſeverall Reflections against this <hi>Hypotheſis</hi> (which this Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor hath fully and civilly anſwered) is one of our own Country men, and a man of no ſmall Eminence, which, perhaps may be one Great REASON why this never learn'd the Engliſh Tongue in publick 'till now.</p>
                  <p>As for the Tranſlation, I hope 'tis per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form'd as near the Author's Mind as poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, ſeeing I have all along, and eſpecially in the most material Places, confin'd my ſelf to the Words of the Author; therefore
<pb facs="tcp:47737:5"/>perhaps ſome places may at their firſt per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uſal appear a little difficult (eſpecially to a Tyro in this Hypotheſis) becauſe they reliſh a little of the French Idiom: however, I hope, It is not ſo much wandred from En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh Senſe, but that thoſe of the meaneſt Capacities may readily enough enjoy the true meaning: Thus by your kind Acceptance of This, you will oblige me to ſerve you fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Yours to ſerve <hi>J.W.</hi> 
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
               <div type="dedication">
                  <pb facs="tcp:47737:6"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:47737:6"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>To</hi> The Deans and Profeſſors of the Faculty of <hi>Caën.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>SIRS,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>'TIS uſual, when we preſent the World with any Work, to chuſe ſome Worthy Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trons, under whoſe Name it may appear, and, who can de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend it againſt the Attacks of En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vy, Prejudice and Ignorance, which are three powerful Enimies to contend againſt, and ſuch as cannot be overcome but by thoſe who have Zeal and Love for Lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, and which are free and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>found in their Underſtandings.
<pb facs="tcp:47737:7"/>'Tis this, Sirs, which has oliged me to offer this little Work to you, and to publiſh it under tho Glory of your Illuſtrious Society: there are none can more advantageouſly defend it than your ſelves, for you diſarm Envy by that Zeal and Love which you have alwaies ſhown to Learning: you vanquiſh Prejudice by that Liberty and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>intereſted Diſpoſition which you retain in Phyſick and Medicine: and you deſtroy Ignorance by that inexhauſtible Fountain of Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing which you injoy. Wilful Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion was never known to reign amongſt you, for you conſider Things with a Solidity and Facul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of Mind truly extraordinary: Reaſon and Experience are the on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Guids you employ in your In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſitions and Underſtandings:
<pb facs="tcp:47737:7"/>Authority has no place with you if it be not accompanied with ſolid Reaſons, and uncontrolable Expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience. In a Word, it ſeems that Nature cannot withdraw her ſelf from your View, nor hath con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceal'd any thing from you.</p>
                  <p>I had inlarged more in your Commendations did not your Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſty reſtrain me, and oblige me to make an End: only with pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſting my ſelf to be all my life time with Reſpect,</p>
                  <closer>
                     <salute>SIRS,</salute>
                     <signed>Your most humble and obedient Servant F. A.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
               <div type="preface">
                  <pb facs="tcp:47737:8"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:47737:8"/>
                  <head>THE Author's Preface.</head>
                  <p>When I reſolved the publiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing my Sentiments on <hi>Acid</hi> and <hi>Alkali,</hi> I could not but doubt my Book would find ſome Cenſures amongst the greater part of thoſe that ſhould read it: and indeed I had little Reaſon to exſpect a more fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vorable Entertainment for the first production of my Genius; ſince I have obſerved the Works of more accompli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed and delicate Wits have not eſcaped the Attaints of Criticks. Beſides there is alſo a particular Conſideration which makes me believe, That is it Inevita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to it, ſince it is not uſual to reaſon according to theſe Principles which are not yet eſtabliſhed. For, it is certain,
<pb facs="tcp:47737:9"/>That there is neceſsary to the inuring ones ſelf to a New Hypotheſis, a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain Meaſure of Time: for, we ſee, That ſuch as have at first esteem'd a Doctrine to be Chimerick and vain, have under their Examination, in Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to refute it, found it poſſible and reaſonable at laſt, and ſo at length, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving made it familiar, have embraced it.</p>
                  <p>All the Explications which I have made of the more curious Phoenome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na's of Nature, are ſo facile and na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural, that they are indeed ſo many Demonſtrations of the Truth of theſe Principles; ſeeing I have not made uſe of any other Proof than thoſe which I have drawn from Reaſon and Expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience.</p>
                  <p>This is that which induced me to Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe under the Names of <hi>Eubulus</hi> and <hi>Pyrophilus;</hi> the first, a man of
<pb facs="tcp:47737:9"/>good Understanding; and the other, a Lover of Experiments. I have choſe the Form of a Dialogue, believing it most proper to instruct, and to give me room to refute all Objections which ſhould be raiſed to the contrary, which I have performed with a few words as was poſſible. I have not ſought any vain Ornaments of Language, becauſe it is the Inclination of my Genius to be more intent on the things themſelves than in the manner of expreſſing them: As for the Reſt, I deſire all thoſe that may happen to have ſome Experiments come to light, that they cannot explain by theſe Principles, not to accuſe the Hypotheſis thereof: But, let ſuch know, That to convince it of Falcity, They ought to demonstrate That it is contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to Experience; and let them alſo remember, That others, or even they themſelves may, which New Lights one
<pb facs="tcp:47737:10"/>day, diſcover the true Cauſe, which they then did not perceive. All thoſe ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Operations which I have unfolded hereby ſhew of what Utility it is in Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſicks; and, if what I have ſaid, be ſo proſperous as to pleaſe the Learned, I intend to ſhew a greater Uſe thereof in Medicine by the Explication of Diſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, and their Symptoms; and the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>midies we may obtain therefrom, with the manner how they act.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="erratum">
                  <p>Errata. <hi>Pag.</hi> 7. <hi>l.</hi> 4. <hi>read</hi> but they. <hi>p.</hi> 9. <hi>l.</hi> 10. <hi>r.</hi> Harts-horn. <hi>p.</hi> 13. <hi>l.</hi> 8. different. <hi>ib. l.</hi> 9.-gulations. <hi>p.</hi> 14. <hi>l.</hi> 3. a ſalt. <hi>ib. l.</hi> 5. diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſſolve it. <hi>p.</hi> 50. <hi>l.</hi> 13. abſorbed. <hi>p.</hi> 56. <hi>l.</hi> 17. it ſelf. <hi>p.</hi> 59. <hi>l.</hi> 9. leaves. <hi>p.</hi> 63. <hi>l.</hi> 20. Retine. <hi>p.</hi> 64. <hi>l.</hi> 22. Retine. <hi>p.</hi> 65. <hi>l.</hi> 16. <hi>dele</hi> of. <hi>p.</hi> 68. <hi>l.</hi> 11 Retine. <hi>p.</hi> 72. <hi>l.</hi> 2. and. <hi>ib. l.</hi> 20. hath. <hi>p.</hi> 79 <hi>l.</hi> 14. or one. <hi>p.</hi> 99. <hi>l.</hi> 19. with. <hi>p.</hi> 101. <hi>l.</hi> 21. <hi>dele</hi> the. <hi>p.</hi> 105 <hi>l.</hi> 21. <hi>dele</hi> the. <hi>p.</hi> 106 <hi>l.</hi> 10. it. <hi>p.</hi> 115. <hi>l.</hi> 1. become. <hi>p.</hi> 127. <hi>l.</hi> 15. you have <hi>p.</hi> 139. <hi>l.</hi> 16. <hi>add</hi> one. <hi>p.</hi> 165. <hi>l.</hi> 3. be as.</p>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="discourse">
                  <pb n="1" facs="tcp:47737:10"/>
                  <head>CHYMICAL <hi>DISCEPTATIONS;</hi> Or, SOME DISCOURSES UPON Acid <hi>and</hi> Alkali.</head>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>EUBU<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>LUS.</speaker>
                     <p>DEar Pyrophilus, We ſhall at laſt arrive at the End of our Errors, and Draw from the Fountain of Nature it ſelf, Thoſe Neceſſary Lights which can make us Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phers.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>PYROPH.</speaker>
                     <p>What ſay you, Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bulus?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="2" facs="tcp:47737:11"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>EUB.</speaker>
                     <p>I ſay nothing but what I can convince you of by evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent Reaſon and certain Expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riments.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>PYR.</speaker>
                     <p>How have you diſcove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red the Truth?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>EUB.</speaker>
                     <p>The Reading good Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors, and the Converſe which I, for ſome time, have had with learned Men, have quite demo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed all my Prejudices, and made me Examine things with as much Freedom and Imparti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ality, as I had before of Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pathy: I have conſtantly ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved, That Authority, eve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> to this preſent time, hath been an Invincible Enemy both to Phyſick and Medicine, and the very Rock upon which all the Famous Men of the paſt Ages have rely'd; and is indeed, at
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:47737:11"/>this day, the Cauſe of ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Sects and different Opinions which we ſee in the Schools: Whereas Reaſon and Experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence are the only True KEYS which can give Admittance in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>o either of theſe Sciences: for, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>o be a Philoſopher, it is abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>utely neceſſary to baniſh Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>hority, and to follow Reaſon <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>nd Experience. I am not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ble ſufficiently to admire the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>roſperous Succeſs and Exact<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>eſs of the Anatomiſts and Chy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>iſts of our Age! The firſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>aving diſcovered to us, in the Body, Parts, Humours and Uſes <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>nknown to the Antients: and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>he Laſt have withdrawn us <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>rom that erroneous Darkneſs wherein the Four Elements and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>heir Firſt and Occult Qualities
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:47737:12"/>had plunged us, giving us Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples as clear as thoſe were ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcure.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>PYR.</speaker>
                     <p>I have alwaies told you That Anatomy and Chymiſtry were great Aſſiſtants to Phyſick and Medicine, and that they en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lighten us much, where we at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain it only by their Experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>EBU.</speaker>
                     <p>I do not deſign to En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertain you here with the New Diſcoveries of Anatomiſts upon Humane Bodies: I ſhall only ſpeak of thoſe which Chy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſts have made us take No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice of, in the Diſſolution of Mixts. Know, that for this Effect, They acknowledg two ſorts of Principles; of which, ſome they call Active Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples; and others they ſtile Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:47737:12"/>Principles. The Active Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>iples are the Cauſes of all the Actions and all the different Motions which are done in Nature: The Paſſive Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>les, on the contrary, are not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>apable of any Action, but ſerve only as Matrixes to the active Principles for them therein to make their Productions.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>PYR.</speaker>
                     <p>VVe cannot deſire an exacter Diſtinction of Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, but how many have you of either.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>EUB.</speaker>
                     <p>There is ſome Contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſy amongſt Chymiſts about the Number of Active Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples; Some will have Three, which they call Salt, Sulphur and Mercury; pretending that theſe are the laſt Bodies they
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:47737:13"/>find in the Reſolution of Mixts. By Mercury they underſtand the moſt ſubtile, moſt penetra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting and moſt aetherial Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance in the Mixt. By Sul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phur, all that which is there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in oleagenous and inflamable and, By Salt, and that is diſſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved in Water, and coagulated by Fire: they ſay, The Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cury or Spirit is the Soul of Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, That it gives Motion and Life to Animals, That it makes Plants grow, brings forth blow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, and ripens Fruits; alſo that it renders Stones and Met<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tals perfect. That the Sulphur or Oil Cauſes the Diverſity of Colours and Odors, the Beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and Deformity of Bodies: and, That the Salt is the cauſe of the Taſtes, Weight, Solidi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:47737:13"/>and hardneſs of Mixts. Others acknowledg that there are Salt, Sulphur and Mercury in all Bodies; they demonſtrate alſo by ſeveral Experiments, That theſe Three Subſtances are compoſed of Two others, a great deal more ſimple, <hi>viz.</hi> of Acid and Alkali Salts, and that Salt, Sulphur and Mercury are no other but theſe Two Salts at liberty or intangl'd: In effect, you ſhall obſerve, That there are Two ſorts of Salts, there are ſome Simples, which are not compounded of any other Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance; and ſome Compounds (as are all the compound Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral Salts, and eſſential Salts of Plants) which are compoſed of ſimple Salts and paſſive Principles, notwithſtanding in
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:47737:14"/>
                        <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                           <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <pb n="7" facs="tcp:47737:14"/>
                        <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                           <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <pb n="8" facs="tcp:47737:15"/>ſuch ſort as the Acid, which is the firſt of theſe ſimple Salts, predominates therein. And theſe Salts are called Salts, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they are diſſolved by Moi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſture, and coagulated by Dri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs.</p>
                     <p>The ſimple Salts are either Alkali or Acid; the Alkali Salts are either Fixed or Volatile: the Acid Salts are alwaies in a Liquor; therefore called Acid Spirits: nevertheleſs, theſe A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cid Spirits are no other but A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cid Salts diſſolved in a little water. The Alkali Salt, on the contrary, is almoſt alwaies in a Body: it is, as I ſaid but even now, either fixed or vola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tile: the fixed Alkali Salt is never elevated by the action of Fire, as Salt of Tartar, and
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:47737:15" rendition="simple:additions"/>all thoſe Salts which are drawn from Plants by Incineration, which we call Lixiviate Salts, as thoſe of Scordium, Tama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>risk, &amp;c. The Volatile Alkali Salt, on the contrary, is eleva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with the leaſt heat of fire, and is drawn chiefly from Ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mals, as the Volatile Salt of Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers, Harts, &amp;c.</p>
                     <p>There are Three Sorts of Mercury or Spirit; an Acid Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, as that of Niter, Allum, Vitriol, &amp;c. A ſharp or biting Spirit, as that of Harts-horn. Urine, Vipers, &amp;c. and a bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning Spirit, as that of Wine, Beer, Cyder, &amp;c. The Acid Spirit is an Acid Salt diſſolved in a little Flegm: The ſharp biting Spirit is an Alkali, vola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tile likewiſe, diſſolved in a little
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:47737:16"/>Flegm and the burning Spirit is a Sulphur; and a Sulphur is an enveloped Acid.</p>
                     <p>All Chymiſts, in effect, agree That there are two paſſive Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples, viz. Water and Earth, or Flegm and Caput Mort.</p>
                     <p>The Water ſerves as a Men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruum and Diſſolvant to the Acid and Alkali Salts; and it is extracted by Diſtillation from thoſe Bodies which contain it.</p>
                     <p>The Earth ſerves as a Bond to theſe Two Salts, it is extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted commonly after the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traction of the Lixivious Salt.</p>
                     <p>It is to be noted, That accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the different Mixture of theſe Four ſorts of Subſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and the different Rangings of their Parts, there are made different Productions in Nature,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:47737:16"/>ſometimes of Animals, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times of Vegetables, and ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times of Minerals.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>PYR</speaker>
                     <p>What do you mean by Acid Salt and Alkali Salt?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>EUB.</speaker>
                     <p>The Acid Salt is eaſily known by the Taſt and Smell, and by the Firmentation which it makes with Alkali's, as Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of Sulphur. This Salt is compoſed of ſmall ſharp poin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted parts, which inſinuate themſelves into the Pores of thoſe Bodies they meet with, and make either a Diſ-union of their Parts, or a Coagulation: for, according to the different Motions, particular Figure. Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tilty or Groſneſs of theſe Points and the diſpoſition of thoſe Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, they either paſs through them with Violence, and ſcat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:47737:17"/>their parts one from ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: or elſe they are Entang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led therein, in ſuch ſort that they loſe their Force and their Motion in them: Remaining very often ſticking to them.</p>
                     <p>We obſerve, in effect, That Acid Salts diſſolve hard Bodies, as Stones, and Metals, (except Gold, which cannot be diſſolv'd but in ſalt Menſtruums:) and coagulates the moſt part of ſoft and fluid Bodies, ſuch as Milk, Blood. &amp;c.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>PYR.</speaker>
                     <p>Then, there are Acid Salts of different Natures?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>EUB.</speaker>
                     <p>There are as many dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent ſorts of Acid ſalts as there are different Bodies in Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture; and though the Particles or Attoms which compoſe them are all ſharp, yet that hinders
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:47737:17"/>not, but they have neverthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs all different Figures, which cauſes all the compound Mine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Salts, in which the Acid ſalt predominates, as Niter, Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triol, &amp;c. and alſo the Eſſenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al Salts of Plants, to take all different Figures in their Coa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gulations according to the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of the Acid which deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mines them, whence ſome are formed Pyramidical, as Niter; others, winding like a Screw, as Vitriol, &amp;c.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>PYR.</speaker>
                     <p>Whence comes it, That Acids diſſolve Silver and other Metals, and do not diſſolve Gold? and, on the contrary, ſalt Liquors diſſolve Gold, and touch neither Silver nor other Metals?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>EUB.</speaker>
                     <p>Gold being almoſt all
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:47737:18"/>Sulphur, cannot be corroded by Acids of what nature ſoever they be, it muſt be ſalt Liquor, and as perfect a Spirit of Salt as can diſſolve; which in Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roſion muſt re-take the Nature of Salt: Silver and other Metals having, on the contrary, more Mercury than Sulphur, can ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver be diſſolved in ſalt Menſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ums, for there is none but Acid Spirits that can diſſolve them. To confirm both to you, You ought to take Notice, That thoſe that work in Slat Petar, after they have extracted it, draw forth yet a Salt, a great deal leſs acid; which is of the Nature of common ſalt, which they call Sal centrique, which when it is Reſolved into a Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quor diſſolves Gold after the
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:47737:18"/>ſame Manner as Spirit of Salt doth, and in corroding re-takes the Nature of Salt, and diſſolves neither Silver nor other Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tals.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>PYR.</speaker>
                     <p>Suppoſe that Gold be almoſt all Sulphur, and then it is eaſy to comprehend, Why it cannot be diſſolved by Acids, but only by ſalt Menſtruums.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>EUB.</speaker>
                     <p>Have you never obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, That when Gold is in flux, if the end of an iron Rod be put therein, it will be calcined and reduced into Scoria? after the ſame manner as if it had been burnt with common Sulphur: and, that Argent vive forſakes all Metals to join it ſelf with Gold, which it renders as brit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle as Glaſs: How ſhould Gold calcine Iron, and be in ſuch wiſe
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:47737:19"/>penetrated by Mercury, as to become brittle as Glaſs, if it did not abound with Sulphur? firſt you know, That Iron can't be calcin'd but by Sulphur, which ſeeing Gold calcines, conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently Gold muſt be a Sul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phur. Secondly, Mercury be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a powerful Metallick Alka<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>li (though impriſoned) which is not joined but with a Sul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phur of its own Nature, would not quit other Metals to be joi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to Gold, if Gold had not more Sulphur than others: and the Mercury renders it not o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe brittle, but becauſe it abſorbs its Sulphur and diſ-u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nites the parts thereof.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>PYR.</speaker>
                     <p>Mercury, nevertheleſs, does not deſtroy the Body of Gold, which it would do, if it
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:47737:19"/>abſorbed the Sulphur, and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>united the parts thereof.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>EUB.</speaker>
                     <p>That is not a Conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence, That becauſe the Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cury abſorbed the Sulphur of Gold, and ſcattered the parts thereof, It muſt therefore de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy it; for the Sulphur of Gold being moſt fixed, and the Mercury, on the contrary, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing moſt volatile, there cannot be made an exact Union betwixt them two, that is to ſay, by ſmall parts; and, the Mercury being caſt into the fire, quits in that moment the Sulphur of the Gold which it had abſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed, and flies away, and the Sulphur of the Gold is re-uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to its own Mercury, and the Gold becomes as hard, as fixed and as ſolid as it was before:
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:47737:20"/>Moreover, how ſhould Gold be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come fulminant, if it did not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bound in Sulphur? The com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition of Aurum fulminans makes us ſufficiently ſenſible of it. They cauſe Gold to diſſolve in Aqua Regis, which they af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards precipitate by little and little with Oil of Tartar made per Deliquium: there is then made a Union of the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kali of Tartar with the Acid ſpirit of the Nitar, which com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed the Aqua fort; and there is produced therefrom a new<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>made Nitar: this Nitar, being united to the Sulphur of the Gold, is inflamed, and produ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceth all thoſe ſurprizing Effects which we take Notice of there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>PYR.</speaker>
                     <p>The Nitar would Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:47737:20"/>theſe Effects alone, or be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing mingled with the Sal Armo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niack or common Salt, which was put into the Aqua Regia.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>EUB.</speaker>
                     <p>Salt-Petar is never in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flamed but when it is mingled with ſome Sulphur; as with common Sulphur in Gun-pou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der and Pulvis fulminans; or with the Sulphur of Antimony when one makes Regulus and Liver, &amp;c. Common ſalt and Sal Armoniack are ſo far from rend'ring Salt-Petar inflamable, that they extinguiſh fire with more force than common Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter doth: it therefore follows, That the Sulphur of the Gold is united with the Salt-Petar, and cauſes this Deflagration.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>PYR.</speaker>
                     <p>We ſee never<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                           <desc>•••</desc>
                        </gap>leſs, That Salt-Petar is inflamed at
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:47737:21"/>the ſame time that one puts it on burning Coals.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>EUB.</speaker>
                     <p>The Salt Petar is not inflamed then, but becauſe it is united to the Sulphur of the Coals: for if one put ſome Salt-Petar into a Crucible and make the Crucible red-hot, it ſimply melts, and is not inflamed but when one caſts ſome Sulphur or ſome Coal thereinto.</p>
                     <p>And, to convince you fully, That Gold contains a great deal more Sulphur than other Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tals; You may take Notice, That one cannot make either Silver, Lead or Tin fulminant, becauſe Theſe Metals have on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly a very little Sulphur, which is wholy abſorbed by their Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cury.</p>
                     <p>There is nothing in the
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:47737:21"/>world which ows not its Birth to Acid Salt: nothing can live, nor be multiplied without it: It is that Soul of the World, of which the Antients have ſo of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten told us:</p>
                     <q>
                        <l>Spiritus intus alit, totam<expan>
                              <am>
                                 <g ref="char:abque"/>
                              </am>
                              <ex>que</ex>
                           </expan> infuſa per artus</l>
                        <l>Mens agitat Molem.</l>
                     </q>
                     <p>The Spirit within, and the Mind infuſed, through the Members nouriſheth and agi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tates the whole Body.</p>
                     <p>In a word, The Acid Salt is the Author of the Conſtruction of every Body, and the abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute Maſter of Alkali Salts, it prints them (as a Seal is made on Wax) with all ſorts of Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racters, and makes thereof ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral different Bodies, accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:47737:22"/>to the diverſity of its points, as we obſerve by the Regeneration of the Eſſential Salts of Plants, and compound Mineral Salts.</p>
                     <p>If one mingles with an Alkali, either fixed or volatile, the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cid Liquor of ſome Vegetable: as for example, Of the grains of Kermes, or Wine, 'till there is not made any more Fermenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and then one philters them through grey Paper, and evaporates the ſuperfluous hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>midity, cauſing them to criſtal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lize in a Cellar or ſome other cool place: there will be made thereof an eſſential Salt of Ker<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes, which hath the ſame Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues with that which is ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily drawn. There will alſo be made a Tartar like that of
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:47737:22"/>Wine, whoſe, ſourneſs is gone.</p>
                     <p>The Acid Spirits of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pound Mineral Salts, as of Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum, Niter, &amp;c. change all ſorts of Alkali's into Salts of their own nature, to wit, into Alum, Niter, &amp;c. like to thoſe from which they were drawn.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>PYR.</speaker>
                     <p>Theſe Experiments are moſt fine, moſt curious and moſt convincing, &amp; this new way of Reaſoning by Deeds, pleaſe me much: but pray give me as clear an Idea of Alkali Salt, as this you have giv'n me of Acid Salt.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>EUB.</speaker>
                     <p>The Alkali Salt is ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſily known, by its fermentati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on with Acids, and by its pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipitating Vitriol of Mars, and other compound Mineral Salts diſſolved in water, except Sea ſalt, in which, the Acid and
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:47737:23"/>Alkali are ſo ſtrictly united that neither the violence of fire, nor the mixture of any other Body can ever diſ-unite them, as I have already ſaid, where I ſpoke of the Diſſoluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Gold in ſalt Menſtruums. I have cauſed you to take No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice, That there are two ſorts of Alkali's, a fixed and a vola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tile; fixed, as Salt of Tartar: Volatile, as the volatile Salt of Vipers.</p>
                     <p>Sal Alkali is extreamly po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous, wholy empty and rough, that is to ſay, whoſe parts are unequal: and, 'tis for this Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, That it whitens Linnen, and cleanſeth Stuffs: It takes out the Filths that are found therein by its Inequalities, and it fills at length its pores there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="25" facs="tcp:47737:23"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>PYR.</speaker>
                     <p>What Proofs have you That Sal Alkali is vacuous and cleanſes Linnen and Stuffs.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>EUB.</speaker>
                     <p>There are ſeveral Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periments which proove both. If Alkali's were not vacuous Salts, How ſhould they be ſo eaſily reſolved into in Liquor, when they are put into a moiſt place? ſince 'tis obſerved that Salts filled with their Acids, as Niter, Alumn, Vitriol, &amp;c. are not Diſſolv'd therein; the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kali of Niter, which has not been ſeparated from its Caput Mort. could not charge it ſelf with an Acid equal to that which was drawn therefrom: Diaphoretick Antimony which has not yet been waſhed, ſhould not augment Weight therin, and ſhould not change its Diapho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retick
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:47737:24"/>retick quality into an Emetick: in a word, Corals, Lead, and divers other Alkali's reverbera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in a violent fire during ſome daies and nights, ſhould not augment a fifth part; and of Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kali's as they were, ſhould not become ſalt, and ſhould ferment ſtill with Acids, as they did be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>before, if Alkali's were not va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuous ſalts, which are eaſily fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led with the Acids of the air and fire. We ſee, notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding all theſe Experiments are true: that the Alkali of Nitar draws out of the Air an Acid of its own Nature, That Antimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nium Diaphoreticum becomes therein Emetick: that reverbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated Corals augment not only in weight, but alſo become Salt, and ferment no more with
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:47737:24"/>Acids, from whence we may very juſtly conclude, That Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cali Salts are vacuous and po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous Salts, which fill them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves with all ſorts of Acids, of what nature ſoever they may be.</p>
                     <p>There are alſo no leſs Proofs that Sal Alkali whitens Linnen and cleanſeth ſtuffs: if you have obſerved, that one cannot make a Lixivium of aſhes wherein this ſalt is wanting, as it is in thoſe of Wood, which hath a long time floated, but only of thoſe in which it abounds, as in the ashes of Oaks, Apple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tree, Broom, &amp;c. and, That the ſalt Salts, as common Salt, can never cleanſe them, becauſe that their Alkali is wholy fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led with its Acid, and ſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:47737:25"/>it cannot fill it ſelf with the filths of the Linnen and Stuffs: I ſhould have no need to bring any other proofs, nor to tell you, That the herb which we call <hi>Saponaire</hi> [Soap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wort] becauſe it is made uſe of to whiten Linnen and Stuffs, cleanſes them on no other ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count, but becauſe it abounds in this Salt.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>PYR.</speaker>
                     <p>I am ſufficiently convin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced by what you have told me. You have already explain'd (where you ſpoke of the Diſſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution of Metals) why Gold cannot be diſſolved but by a Salt Liquor, and Silver and the other Metals, on the contrary, but by an Acid Liquor: I would willingly you Explained to me, Why Acids do not precipitate
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:47737:25"/>Vitriol of Mars diſſolv'd in wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, as Alkali's do: and, as they, on the contrary, precipi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate equal with them, Mercury ſublimate diſſolved in common water, &amp; ☿ diſſolv'd in Aq. fort.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>EUB.</speaker>
                     <p>It is eaſy to give you a Reaſon for all theſe different Ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects: for, Little do you conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the manner by which theſe Praecipitations are performed. Alkali's, as well fixed as vola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tile precipitate all theſe Diſſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutions, becauſe they abſorb the Acids which hold the Iron and Mercury in Diſſolution; and in this Manner the Iron and the Mercury being no longer detai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned nor agitated by the points of thoſe Acids, are precipitated and fall by their own weight to the bottom of the Veſſel
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:47737:26"/>which contains them: It hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pens much otherwiſe in the precipitation which Acids make of corroſive ſublimate diſſolv'd in common Water, and Mercu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry diſſolved in Aqua fort. for there is not made any Union of Acid with Alkali, but only a Confuſion of Acid with Acid: and this precipitation happens only becauſe the Acids of Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, Vitriol and common ſalt which had ſublimed the Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cury, and thoſe of the Aqua fort. which had diſſolv'd it, were not able to penetrate, nor unite themſelves intimately with it: which cauſes that a new Acid eaſily ſhakes them &amp; makes them at the ſame time to quit their hold; thus is the ☿ precipitated: This is the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:47737:26"/>why Acids can never preci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitate Vitriol of Mars diſſolv'd in water, becauſe there is ſo perfect and ſtrict a Union be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween its Acid and Alkali, that there is not found the leaſt pore which is not filled, in ſuch man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, That a New Acid not fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding therein any vacuous place can never diſ-unite them.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>PYR.</speaker>
                     <p>I do not yet well under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand how Acids which hold a Body in Diſſolution, can quit it to join themſelves to another.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>EUB.</speaker>
                     <p>Experience will preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly make you comprehend it, for if one caſts upon a Solution of Vitriol of Mars and upon that of Mercury ſublimate an Alkali, whatſoever it be, there will be made at that inſtant a Precipitate: and, if after ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:47737:27"/>put an Alkali to it, there is immediately put, an Acid, there will not be made any pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipitate, but the ſolution will remain as clear as it was be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore; becauſe the Acid which was put laſt thereto, joining it ſelf to the Alkali which was put to it before, hinders con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently that that Alkali can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not abſorb the Acid which held the Mercury and Iron in diſſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: if this Precipitation of Vitriol or Mars, and Mercury diſſolved by Acid Spirits and precipitated afterwards with Alkali's, was made after any other manner than that which I have already told you, it ſhould be all one whether one put an Acid thereto after there was an Alcali caſt into it; or,
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:47737:27"/>that one put none, the which notwithſtanding happens not, for the Acid which was put thereto, joining it ſelf to the Alkali which was put thereto before, hinders by that means that the Alkali could not ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſorb the Acid ſpirits, which held the Mercury and Iron in diſiolution.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>PYR.</speaker>
                     <p>All your Experiments convince me ſtrongly of that which you have told me concerning Acid and Alkali Salts; but, as it is not ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent to Eſtabliſh Principles, on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to tell what they are, and what they do: It is therefore very needful it be proov'd that they Exiſt, that they are found in all Bodies, and that they are Principles therto, that's to ſay,
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:47737:28"/>That all Bodies are reſolv'd in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them; and, that they are not reſolv'd into any other ſubſtance: and, 'Tis this that I could wiſh you would plainly ſhew me, concerning theſe two Salts, if it be poſſible.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>EUB.</speaker>
                     <p>You have none but Animals, Vegetables and Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerals to examine, and you ſhall not find one of them, in which theſe two Salts are not to be met withal, and in which they are not Principles.</p>
                     <p>The Volatile Alkali's which are drawn in abundance from the Blood, Fleſh, Horns and Bones of Animals, which fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments with all Acids, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipitates Vitriol of Mars diſſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved in water, do they not prove, There is exceſs of Alkali
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:47737:28"/>therein? and the different Acid Juices which are ſeparated from their Bodies, as Spittle which mortifies Mercury, it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a powerful Alkali, which cannot be ſo mortified but by an Acid: and, as the Acid of the Stomach curdles Milk when one drinks it faſting, the which is plainly perceived by Vomit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it up again, almoſt as ſoon as it was taken, and Milk cannot be coagulated but by an Acid. Fleſh, alſo Blood and Milk which grow ſower when they begin to corrupt, prove ſufficiently, That there is ſome Acid Salt in Animals.</p>
                     <p>Is there a Vegetable in which theſe two Salts are not found? the ſimple Fermentation which Vegetable Juices make, ſhould
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:47737:29"/>be ſufficient to convince you of it; for Fermentation, as I ſhall tell you hereafter, cannot be made but by the meeting of theſe two Salts. Alſo there is not a Vegetable from which we do not draw a great quantity of Alkali, and which does not give, when it begins to corrupt ſufficiently ſenſible ſigns of its Acidity. How alſo ſhould we be able to draw an Eſſential ſalt from Plants, if they had not Acid and Alkali, ſeeing Eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſential ſalts are no other (as I gave you to obſerve, when I ſpake of the Regeneration of Salts) than theſe two Salts joi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned together.</p>
                     <p>Do they not draw alſo an Acid and Alkali from Minerals? compound Mineral Salts, as Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triol,
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:47737:29"/>Alum, Niter, &amp;c. give us an Acid in diſſolution; and leave us an Alkali in the Caput Mort. Calcined ſtones, as Calx vive, are not fermented when they are diſſolved in water; but becauſe they contain each of theſe two Salts: Hath not com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Sulphur its Acid, which they draw, per Campanum, in burning it, and which elevates Mercury into Cinaber? hath it not alſo its Alkali which re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mains in the Caput Mort? Is there not Acid and Alkali in Antimony, as we obſerve in the Compoſition of its Butter? E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qual parts of Antimony and Mercury ſublimate they mingle together, which they put in a Retort and commit to the fire. Then the Acid ſpirits,
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:47737:30"/>which had ſublimed the Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cury, quits it to join it ſelf to the mercurial Part or Alkali of the Antimony, and the Sul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phur or Acid of the Antimony elevates the Mercury into Cin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nabat. Have not the Metals alſo their Acid and Alkali? Gold abounds in Sulphur which is Acid, and it hath a Mercury which retains this Sulphur, and unites it ſelf inti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mately to it, Silver and the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Metals have a Mercury which ferments with ſpirit of Niter which is Acid and a Sul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phur which hinders the volati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, and fluidity of this Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cury.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>PYR.</speaker>
                     <p>May not the fire pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce theſe Salts alſo from the moſt part of thoſe Bodies from
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:47737:30"/>which they are drawn.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>EUB.</speaker>
                     <p>No; for when one has once drawn the Salt from A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhes, calcine them never ſo wel, they will never give others, no more than floted wood [that is. I ſuppoſe, Wood that has lain in water till it is rotten] rotten wood, and Plants expo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed ſome daies and nights to the Aier, becauſe their ſalts have been diſſolv'd in the air and water, and are conſequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly drawn out from their Bodies. It ſhould not happen ſo, if the fire had produced thoſe two Salts; for, then at all times, whether after Putrifaction or Calcination the fire ſhould al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways, produce ſome new ſalt, and one body would give no more than another; the which
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:47737:31"/>is contrary to Experien<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>e, as you ſee.</p>
                     <p>The Acidity of Blood, Milk and Fleſh is natural to them, and thoſe different Acid Juices which we find in the Bodies of Animals are ſeparated there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>from without Artifice, and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the help of fire.</p>
                     <p>The Fermentation which Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>getable Juices make, is done of it ſelf.</p>
                     <p>In a word; The Acids and Alkali's of compound Mineral ſalts, ſeparated one from the other by the means of fire, would never recompoſe the ſame ſalts, when one reunites them together, if the Fire had produced them: for, what pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion, what relation ſhould theſe new Productions of the
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:47737:31"/>fire have with the Principles which compoſe theſe ſalts, to cauſe that theſe Productions ſhould regenerate ſalts, as natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral as Niter, Alum, Sal-gem, &amp;c.</p>
                     <p>You ſee plainly by all theſe Experiments, That the Fire does not produce in Bodies the Salts which we draw there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>from, but that theſe Salts are actually found therein. There remains no more, but that I ſhew you they are Principles thereto.</p>
                     <p>There are commonly drawn from all Bodies, three different Subſtances, to which are given (as I have already ſaid) the names of Salt, Sulphur and Mercury, which are pretended to be the laſt Bodies, which are
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:47737:32"/>found in the Reſolution of Mixts: but Experience hath at length diſcovered, That theſe Three Subſtances were compo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed of Acid Salt and Alkali Salt; and, that theſe two Salts are not compoſed of any other ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance and by conſequence, they ought to be Principles.</p>
                     <p>For, though the Artiſt work as much as he will, he may ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſily find the means to reduce the Salt, Sulphur and Mercury into our Two Salts but he will never find the Knack to reduce theſe two Salts into any other Subſtances; and though he make uſe of the ſame two In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firnments which he uſed for the reducing the other Three ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances into theſe Two Salts, to wit, Fire and Water: notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:47737:32"/>ſtanding he ſhall never be able to make that the Acid Salt be no more Acid Salt, nor the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kali Salt, Sal Alkali.</p>
                     <p>I have occaſioned you to take Notice, that there are two ſorts of Salts, namely, an Acid Salt and an Alkali; That there are Three ſorts of Spirits or Mercuries, an Acid ſpirit, a ſharp [biting] ſpirit, and a bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning ſpirit: that the Acid ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit was an Acid Salt, diſſolv'd in a little flegm; the ſharp ſpirit a volatile Alkali diſſolved alſo in a little flegm; and the burn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſpirit, a Sulphur, and Sul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phur an inveloped Acid, I have now no more to do, but to bring you ſome Experiments to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince you of this Truth.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <div n="1" type="experiment">
                     <pb n="44" facs="tcp:47737:33"/>
                     <head>
                        <hi>I. EXPERIMENT.</hi> Which proves that Acià Spirits are no other than Acid Salis diſſolved in ſome flegm.</head>
                     <p>An Acid Spirit ferments it ſelf with all Alkali's, and makes thereof Salts of the ſame na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture with thoſe from which it was drawn, as the Spirit of Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, &amp;c.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="2" type="experiment">
                     <head>
                        <hi>II. EXPERIMENT.</hi> A ſharp Spirit is a Volatile Alkali diſſolved in ſome Flegm.</head>
                     <p>All ſharp ſpirits ferment themſelves with Acids, and precipitates Vitriol of Mars
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:47737:33"/>diſſolved in water, as the vola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tile ſpirit of ſal-Armoniack, &amp;c.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="3" type="experiment">
                     <head>
                        <hi>III. EXPERIMENT</hi> Which proves that burning ſpirits are Sulphurs.</head>
                     <p>Plants give a great deal of Oil, and a little ſpirit, before they are fermented: and they give, on the contrary, a great deal of ſpirit, and a very little Oil after they are fermented, becauſe the parts thereof un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>looſe themſelves and diſ-intan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gle themſelves one from the other in the time of Fermenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and remain bound and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tangled one in the other be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Fermentation was made, which clearly ſhews that
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:47737:34"/>a burning ſpirit is a vegetable ſulphur, but much leſs intan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gled than the other ſulphurs of Vegetables.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="4" type="experiment">
                     <head>
                        <hi>IV. EXPERIMENT</hi> Which proves the ſame.</head>
                     <p>Experience ſhews us, That burning ſpirits expoſed to the air for ſome time, are changed into Oils of the ſame nature as thoſe of the Plants from which they were drawn.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="5" type="experiment">
                     <head>
                        <hi>V. EXPERIMENT</hi> Which demonſtrates that burning Spirits are envelloped Acids.</head>
                     <p>There is drawn from ſalt
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:47737:34"/>of Saturn a burning ſpirit of the ſame nature as ſpirit of Wine, this ſpirit cannot come but from the Acid of the diſtilled Vinegar, which entred into the Compoſition of the ſalt of Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn, whoſe parts are bound and intangled one in the other.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="6" type="experiment">
                     <head>
                        <hi>VI. EXPERIMENT</hi> Which proves that Oyles of Vege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tables are envelloped Acids.</head>
                     <p>Oyl corrodes Copper and turns it into Verdigriſe: there are none but Acids which can produce this Effect: and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore conſequently Oil ought to be Acid.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="7" type="experiment">
                     <pb n="48" facs="tcp:47737:35"/>
                     <head>
                        <hi>VII. EXPERIMENT</hi> Which proves the ſame.</head>
                     <p>Fire is an Oyl whoſe parts are unwrapped, and in a moſt Violent Agitation and Motion: fire is Acid, (ſince it renders Corals Salt) Oyl which is the matter thereof ought then to be Acid.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="8" type="experiment">
                     <head>
                        <hi>VIII. EXPERIMENT</hi> Which proves the ſame.</head>
                     <p>Soap does furniſh us ſtill with a moſt convincing Proof, That Oils of Vegetables are en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veloped Acids: Soap is made with three parts of Alkali and
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:47737:35"/>two of Oil, which two mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters are mingled together, and then boiled; and there comes therefrom a ſalt body which is Soap: you know that ſalt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs comes from the mixture of Acid with Alkali: and, that conſequently, ſeing ſoap is ſalt, the Soap ought not only to have Alkali in it, but alſo A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cid, the Acid cannot be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municated to it but by the Oil which was put thereto, which Acid unwraps it ſelf in the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kali, which was joined thereto: it muſt be therefore that Oil is an envelloped Acid.</p>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>PYR.</speaker>
                        <p>It may be alſo, Tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> the Fire communicated this ſaltneſs to the ſoap, as it did to the Corals; for, you have al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready told me, That when one
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:47737:36"/>reverberates them in a violent fire for ſome daies and nights, they become intirely Salt, and ferment no more with Acids.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>EUB.</speaker>
                        <p>The ſame thing can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be ſaid of ſoap, as of Corals; becauſe one muſt reverberate the Coral ſix daies and nights to render them ſalt, and the ſaltneſs of Soap is communica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to it in a ſhort time, even as ſoon as the Acid of the Oil is diſ-enveloped and abſrobed by the Alkali which was put thereto, likewiſe the ſoap aug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments not in weight on the fire, as the Corals do, they augmen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting a fifth part.</p>
                     </sp>
                  </div>
                  <div n="9" type="experiment">
                     <pb n="51" facs="tcp:47737:36"/>
                     <head>
                        <hi>IX. EXPERIMENT,</hi> Which proves that the Fats and Suets of Animals are envelloped Acids.</head>
                     <p>Soap is made with the ſuet of Animals, after the ſame man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner as it is with the Oils of Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>getables: It muſt be therefore that the Fats and Suets of Ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mals may be envelloped Acids, as the Oils of Vegetables are.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="10" type="experiment">
                     <head>
                        <hi>X. EXPERIMENT,</hi> Which proves the ſame.</head>
                     <p>The flame of Fats and Suets is Acid: it deſtroies Iron, and reduces it into Scoria's, &amp;c.
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:47737:37"/>Greaſe's and Suets ought then to be Acids.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="11" type="experiment">
                     <head>
                        <hi>XI. EXPERIMENT,</hi> Which proves that the Sulphurs of Minerals and Metals are envel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loped Acids.</head>
                     <p>Sulphur of Antimony ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vates Mercury into Cinnabar, as we obſerved in the Compoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of its Butter; How ſhould the Sulphur of Antimony ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate Mercury (which is an Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kali) into Cinnabar, if it were not Acid? It follows therefore that the Sulphur of Antimony is acid.</p>
                     <p>Common Sulphur elevates Mercury into Cinnaber, and it may be made uſe of for the
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:47737:37"/>poſition of Soap, as well as the Oils of Vegetables, and Fats of Animals: In a word, the Sul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phur of Gold is acid, ſince it produceth the ſame Effects as Acids do, for it calcines Iron which cannot be calcin'd but by Acids, &amp;c. The Sulphurs of Minerals and Metals are then envelloped Acids.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="dialogue__cont.">
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>PYR.</speaker>
                        <p>In Truth, Theſe Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples are moſt ſenſible and pal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>EUB.</speaker>
                        <p>This is not yet enough to have diſcovered thus much to you concerning Acid Salt &amp; Alkali Salt in particular: but 'tis needful that I preſs the thing more home, and that I make you know what theſe II Salts are capable to do, when they are once united. Theſe
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:47737:38"/>two Salts are in regard one of the other, as the Soul is in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard of the Body, and the Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy in reſpect of the Soul: The the Acid Salt is the Soul which animates and vivifies the Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, and the Alkali Salt is the Body which receiveth the Soul and unites it ſelf ſo intimately therewith: that this Soul can be nothing without this Body, nor this Body without this Soul. When they are once in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timately united, as we obſerve in common Salt: it is impoſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to ſeparate them one from the other: and though theſe two Salts ſeem, at firſt ſight, to have an Antipathy, one againſt the other, by the Fermentati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on which they make when they meet: Nevertheleſs they
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:47737:38"/>embrace and unite in ſuch wiſe together, that, very far from deſtroying themſelves, they are coagulated, and make no more, but one and the ſame Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy. And, it may be ſaid there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of as the Incomparable <hi>Hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crates</hi> hath ſaid in his Book of DIET, ſpeaking of Fire and Water, that though theſe two Elements differ in Quality, ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertheleſs, they agree in uſe, That they are ſufficient for all Bodies and for themſelves, but neither the one nor the other ſeparated can be ſufficient nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther for any other body nor for it ſelf.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Constituuntur</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>tum Ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mantia tum alia omnia, tum homo ipſe ex duobus differentibus quidem facultate, Concordibus vero &amp;
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:47737:39"/>commodis uſu; haec ambo ſimul ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficientia ſunt tum aliis omnibus, tum mutuo ſibi ipſis, Utrumvis ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ro ſeorſum neque ulli alteri neque ſibi ipſi ſufficiens est.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>All living creatures (ſaith he) as well all other things as Man himſelf, are conſtituted of two Principles different in Faculty, but concording and fit for uſe: Theſe two together are ſufficient for all other things, as well as for them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, but either of them ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally and apart is neither ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient for any other nor for themſelves.</p>
                     <p>Theſe two Salts are never at reſt, if they be not united one with the other, and as ſoon as they are once united, have no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but love and ſympathy
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:47737:39"/>one for the other: which we take notice of by an Infinity of Experiments, as by the ſympa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thetical Inks.</p>
                     <div n="1" type="formula">
                        <head>The first Sympathetical Ink.</head>
                        <p>THere muſt be made two dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent Liquors in two ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate Veſſels.</p>
                        <p>The firſt, which is that we muſt write with, is made with diſtilled Vinegar and Ceruſe, which muſt be made to boil together for the ſpace of an hour in a well ſtopt Vial, then filter them through grey Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, and reſerve the Liquor which comes therefrom in an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other bottle well ſtopt.</p>
                        <p>The Second which cauſeth the writing to appear, is made
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:47737:40"/>with Calx Vive, Orpiment and common water, after the ſame manner as the former.</p>
                        <p>We Write with the firſt of theſe two Liquors, and we ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply upon the Writing a paper imbued with the laſt; the Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting that was inviſible appears at that inſtant as black as if it had been writ with the beſt Ink in the world.</p>
                        <p>For to underſtand clearly the cauſe of this ſo ſurpriſing Effect; we muſt take Notice, That the Calx vive and Orpiment a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bound with Alkali, and that theſe Alkali's wherewith we did imbue the Paper, quits the Paper to abſorb the Acid of the Vinegar, and ſo the Writing appears.</p>
                        <p>But that which is more ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſing
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:47737:40"/>is, That the Alkali's of Calx Vive and Orpiment can paſs through a Ream of Paper, a Table, and a Wall, to abſorb the Acids of the Vinegar, which is obſerved by the Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting which at the ſame time ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears, and by the Impreſſion and odour which it e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>aves on the Paper.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="2" type="formula">
                        <head>The Second Sympathetical Ink.</head>
                        <p>WE muſt write with an Ink made of Cork Coals and Gum-Arabick, and the Writing will appear moſt black; then rub this Writing with the Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quor made with the Calx Vive and Orpiment, and it wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>l at that inſtant diſappear, and will never reappear, if it be not rub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:47737:41"/>with ſome acid liquor, as with that which was made with diſtilled Vinegar and Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſe.</p>
                        <p>The Alkali's of Calx Vive, and Orpiment abſorb (as you ſee) the Acid of the Cork Coals and Gum Arabick, and ſo ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>literates the Writing, which reappears as ſoon as it is rub'd with ſome Acid liquor, becauſe the Alkali which had abſorbed the Acid of the Ink, quits it to abſorb that which one caſts thereto: thus the Writing re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>appears.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="3" type="formula">
                        <head>The Third Sympathetical Ink.</head>
                        <p>THis third Experiment teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the way to tranſcribe in a Moment all ſort of Books,
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:47737:41"/>and Characters, and to draw out all ſorts of Prints.</p>
                        <p>Take Venice Soap cut into little bits, and Oak-aſhes equal parts, and about as much Calx vive, cauſe them to boil in a new bottle with common wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, then philter them through grey Paper, and rub with a fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther dipt in the Liquor which ſhall come therefrom the Book or Image which you would draw, put ſome white Paper which you ſhal alſo rub with the ſaid Liquor, between each leaf of the Book; put this Book between two preſſures, &amp; in a quarter of an hour it wil be drawn; the Letters or Picture not being in any wiſe hurt.</p>
                        <p>The Reaſon of this Experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is, That the Acid of the
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:47737:42" rendition="simple:additions"/>Ink, which always over-pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers its Alkali, and which in proceſs of time blots out the print or writing, does fortify the Acid of the Liquor, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with we did imbue the Paper, in uniting it ſelf with its Alka<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>li, and conſequently prints all the Characters of the Book on the Paper, after ſuch faſhion as they are in the book printed or written, only as much Acid as the Alkali thereof could ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſorb; ſo that the writing be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes fairer and nearer than it was before.</p>
                        <p>It is for the ſame Reaſon that Acids, as ſpirit of Niter, obliterates writing, becauſe they choke the Alkali thereof; and, that ſtrong Alkali's, ſuch as the Infuſion of Gall-nuts,
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:47737:42"/>cauſes them to reappear when they are rub'd therewith, and renews antient defaced Books and Writings, becauſe they charge themſelves with the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cid which had blotted out the Writing.</p>
                        <p>Theſe two Salts are at reſt as ſoon as they are united: they cauſe the Diverſities of all the Phenomena's which we ſee in Nature. They are the cauſe of the permanent colors which we behold, and of the Odours we ſcent, and Savors which we perceive; for, according to the different Mixture of theſe two Salts, the different Nature and the different Ranging of their parts, the Retain is different<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſtruck, and we behold diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent Colours, and the olfacto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Nerves &amp; papillous Nerves
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:47737:43"/>of the Tongue are alſo diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rently ſtruck, and we taſte, and ſmell differently.</p>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>PYR.</speaker>
                           <p>I earneſtly deſire you would yet more explain to me how Acid Salt and Alkali Salt joined together cauſe in us all theſe different Sentiments <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                                 <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                              </gap> of which you tell us.</p>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>EUB.</speaker>
                           <p>Whether the diverſity of Colors which we behold comes only from the divers Reflect<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>
                              <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Light; whether they com only from the different Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion which a coloured Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy makes upon the Air, and the Air upon the optick Nerves: or, whether laſtly, they may be no other but Attoms or Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puſcles which go out continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally from Bodies, and ſtriking the Retain, cauſe in us different
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:47737:43"/>colours; it's alwaies conſtant, That the principal cauſe of permanent colours comes only from the different Nature, and different Mixture of Acid Salts with Alkali Salts, which we may obſerve by divers Experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.</p>
                        </sp>
                     </div>
                     <div n="1" type="experiment">
                        <head>The firſt Experiment.</head>
                        <p>ALl Acids deſtroy blew co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lours, and all Alkali's make them re-appear.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="2" type="experiment">
                        <head>The Second Experiment.</head>
                        <p>SYrup of Violets, which is a Compoſition of Acid and Alkali, becoms of the faireſt Green in the world when it is mingled with ſome Alkali, as
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:47737:44"/>with oil of Tartar made <hi>per de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liquium;</hi> and reddiſh, when ſome Acid is mingled there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="3" type="experiment">
                        <head>The Third Experiment.</head>
                        <p>OIl of Vitriol is a powerful Acid, makes a black Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition with an Infuſion of Gall-nuts which is a powerful Alkali.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="4" type="experiment">
                        <head>The Fourth Experiment.</head>
                        <p>A Decoction of Red Roſes be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes ruddy by Mixture with Acids, and black by Mix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture with Alkali's.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="5" type="experiment">
                        <pb n="67" facs="tcp:47737:44"/>
                        <head>The Fifth Experiment.</head>
                        <p>MErcury is elevated into Cinabar by common Sul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phur and becomes a fair Red: and the ſame Mercury ſubli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, diſſolv'd in water, and then precipitated by Alkali's, falls down in a pouder, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times red, ſomtimes white, yel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low, citrine, &amp;c. according to the nature of the Alkali which pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipitated it, and as the Alkali abſorbed more or leſs the Acid which held the Mercury in Diſſolution.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="6" type="experiment">
                        <head>The Sixth Experiment.</head>
                        <p>SSpirit of Niter, which is a great Acid, renders the Jui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:47737:45"/>of Herbs, which abound in volatile Alkali, as white as Milk.</p>
                        <p>Diſtilled Vinegar doth the ſame with Litharge in the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition of Lac Virginis.</p>
                        <p>The Smell is an affection of the olfactory Nerves, and the Taſt is alſo one of the papillous Nerves of the Tongue, as co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lours are of the Retain. There is ſo great a Relation between the Taſte and Smell, that thoſe things which are agreeable to the Smell are alſo almoſt al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes to the Taſte: Whence it comes, That the moſt part of Animals ſmell their Aliments before they taſt them, and they do not eat them except they find them agreeable to their Smell, as we may take notice
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:47737:45"/>of it in Apes. All the Diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence between theſe two Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes is, That the Particles which cauſe us to Smell are a great deal more ſubtile and thin than thoſe which cauſe us to Taſte.</p>
                        <p>As there are no Colors which we do not behold but by the different mixtures of Acids with Alkali's; ſo there is alſo no Savour nor Odors which we do not perceive according to the divers Mixture of theſe two Salts.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="1" type="experiment">
                        <head>
                           <hi>1. EXPERIMENT,</hi> Which proves that Odours come from Acid and Alkali.</head>
                        <p>OIl of Roſes drawn by Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tillation (which is an en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velloped
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:47737:46"/>Acid) mixt with a ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient great quantity of water hath almoſt no odour, but min<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gled with Salt of Tartar, which is a powerful Alkali, it makes a fluid Compoſition, ſome drops of which being mingled with a quantity of water, makes the water one of the moſt delecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble odours in the World.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="2" type="experiment">
                        <head>
                           <hi>2. EXPERIMENT,</hi> Which proves the ſame.</head>
                        <p>SUlphurs of Minerals which are envellopod Acids, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to be diſſolved by Fire, or ſome other Diſſolvant, caſt forth an odour as ſtinking as that of the Oil of Roſes drawn by Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtillation, but mixt with ſome Alkali it's pleaſant.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="3" type="experiment">
                        <pb n="71" facs="tcp:47737:46"/>
                        <head>
                           <hi>3. EXPERIMENT,</hi> Which proves that the Difference of Taſts comes from the Diver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity of Acids and Alkali's.</head>
                        <p>EXperience ſhews us, That Saltneſs comes from the Mixture of Acids with Alka<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>li's: Soap which is ſalt gives us a familiar example thereof; It is made with pure Alkali's, and Oil which is an enveloped Acid.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="4" type="experiment">
                        <head>
                           <hi>4. EXPERIMENT.</hi> Which proves that the Diverſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of Savours depends upon the
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:47737:47" rendition="simple:additions"/>different Mixture and particular nature of Acids <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                              <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                           </gap> Alkali's.</head>
                        <p>SIlver reduced into Criſtals by ſpirit of Niter, which is a powerful Acid, become of an extream bitter Taſt: Lead, on the contrary, diſſolved in di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtilled Vinegar and reduced in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to ſalt, acquires the ſweetneſs of ſugar, &amp;c.</p>
                        <p>I could bring ſeveral other Experiments to prove that the diverſity of Odors and Savours depends upon the different Mixture of Acid and Alkali: But, tho' I have diſcourſed you thereof elſewhere, I ſhall yet bring you one more ſufficient<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly familiar: which is that of Wine: Wine having another Taſt and another Smell before
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:47737:47" rendition="simple:additions"/>it is fermented, than it has when it is fermenting, or after it is Fermented, for it changes by little and little its green Taſte into a pleſanter, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes at laſt ſour, and loſeth its temperament of Wine; and all theſe changes happens to it according <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                              <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                           </gap> the Acids and Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kalies which are found therein are more or leſs intangled, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                              <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                           </gap> as one of them is more or leſs exalted, and there is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt no odor or ſavor through which it doth not paſs before it grows four.</p>
                        <p>There remains no more but that I ſpeak two words of the paſſive Principles.</p>
                        <p>The Water is the firſt of theſe Principles, it ſerves (as I
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:47737:48"/>have already told you) as a Vehicle to the Acid and Alkali ſalts; it ſerves alſo to diſſolve them, and put them in Motion, becauſe Salts act not except they are diſſolved, <hi>Salia non agunt niſi diſſoluta.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>Water cauſes the Deſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Mixts, when it is found therein in too great a quanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, as it compacts them; and ſtrictly unites their parts when it is found therein in a leſſer quantity; and it fills up the empty ſpaces, which it meets with therein.</p>
                        <p>The Earth or Caput Mort. on the contrary being ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treamly porous and light, makes a great many vacancies in Bodies wherein it is found; but, on the other hand, it hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:47737:48" rendition="simple:additions"/>that thoſe bodies be not deſtroy'd by the abundance of flegm.</p>
                        <p>It is unneceſſary to bring you a great many Experiments to prove that Water and Earth are found in all Bodies, and, That they are Principles thereto, but without any action: I believe you are ſufficiently convinced thereof, and have ſeveral times obſerv'd, That there is no Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy from which we cannot draw ſome Flegm by Diſtillation, and which leave not ſome Earth after Calcination; and though we work never ſo much on Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter and Earth, it is Impoſſi to draw any other thing there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>from but water and Earth. You are not ignorant alſo. That rot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten wood which hath no Acid
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:47737:49" rendition="simple:additions"/>and Alkali Salts, and which hath nothing but ſome Flegm and Earth, hath no more any action.</p>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>PYR.</speaker>
                           <p>I could wiſh you would a little longer explain what you mean by the words <hi>Fermentation</hi> and <hi>Precipita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> whereof you make uſe ſo often.</p>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>EUBUL.</speaker>
                           <p>By the Word <hi>Fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentation,</hi> I mean an Internal Motion of all the parts of Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies which are fermented in ſuch Manner that they take no more the ſame place nor ſcitua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion as they had before, and that they change conſequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, or at leaſt alter very much the nature of the bodies which are fermented: as for the difference of Efferveſcence,
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:47737:49"/>in which there is made only a ſimple Motion of the integral parts of Mixts by the force of ſome exteriour Agent, as Fire; the which parts re-take after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the ſame ſcituation which thy occupied before, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs their natures and qualities be in any wiſe changed.</p>
                        </sp>
                        <p>There are ſeveral ſorts of fermentations in Nature; ſome are made with Efferveſcence, as that which happens upon the mixture of Oil of Vitriol with Oil of Tartar: and others are made without Efferveſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence, as it happens in an Eg which a Hen hatcheth: and in common Water, when one caſts thereinto ſome Drops of well-deflegm'd Spirit of Vitriol, and this Fermentation is known on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:47737:50"/>by the Heat which we feel at that inſtant: There are ſome which are made without Heat, as that which is made of Vitri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ol diſſolved in water with Oil of Tartar: There are ſome which are made with Fires and Flames, as the Fermentation which is made of Calx Vive in the time it is ſprinkled with a little Vinegar: and others which are without Fire or flame, as are the ordinary Fermentati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. There are ſtill ſome ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible and inſenſible; ſenſible, as the Fermentation of Spirit of Niter with Oil of Tartar: and inſenſible, as that of Wine, which ſours.</p>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>PYR.</speaker>
                           <p>Whence comes it that there are ſo many ſorts of Fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentations?</p>
                        </sp>
                        <pb n="79" facs="tcp:47737:50"/>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>EUB.</speaker>
                           <p>Either Bodies are fermen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted of themſelves, as Wine; or they are fermented by means of a Ferment, as Dough with Leven; either the Acid Salts and Alkali Salts are Exalted, or elſe they are Intangled one in the other: and, in the Paſſive principles, one of them is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alted, and the other Intangled; or, one of them is in a great quantity, and the other in a ſmall quantity.</p>
                           <p>If the Acid Salts and Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kali Salts are each as pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erful as the other, the Fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentation cannot be made without Heat and Efferveſcence, as of ſpirit of Niter with oil of Tartar; if, on the contrary, one of theſe two Salts is weak and the other ſtrong, as are the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kali
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:47737:51"/>of Water, and the Acid of Oil of Vitriol well deflegm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, there is only made a little heat without efferveſcence: if the Acid, which is mingled with the Alkali, is diſ-intangled from its own Alkali and paſſive Principles; as the Acid of Oil of Vitriol, there is made a Fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentation with Heat and Effer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veſcence: and, if on the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary, the Acid is intangled, as in Vitriol in its Body; there is only made a Fermentation with Efferveſcence without Heat: In like manner, if theſe two Salts are exalted and diſ-intangled one from the other, and from the paſſive Principles, they take fire at the ſame time that they ferment, as Calx vive doth when it is ſprinkled with ſome
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:47737:51"/>Vinegar. In a word, if theſe two Salts are weak, the Fermen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation is inſenſible.</p>
                           <p>There are few Fermentations made, but there is at the ſame time made a Precipitation; tho' there are ſeveral Precipitations made without Fermentation, as in the Precipitation which is done by Acids of Mercury ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>limate diſſolved in Water.</p>
                        </sp>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Precipitation</hi> is a Diſ-uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of a diſſolved Body from its diſſolvant, in ſuch manner that being ſeparated therefrom it falls by its own weight to the bottom of the veſſel which contain'd it.</p>
                        <p>Precipitation is made ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral wayes; for, either it is an Acid which holds an Alkali in
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:47737:52"/>diſſolution; or, its an Acid which is diſſolved by an Alka<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>li, as it happens in the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition of Regulus of Antimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, in which the Sulphur of Antimony, which is an Acid, is ſeparated from the Regulus, and remains in the Foeces diſſolved by the Alkali's of Tartar and Niter. If it is an Acid which holds an Alkali in diſſolution; where the union is ſo perfect that there is not the leaſt Pore empty (as in all the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pound Mineral Salts, as Vitriol) the Precipitation cannot be made but by an Alkali; or elſe, where the union is not ſo per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect, and there remains a great many Pores which are not filled by this Acid, as in cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roſive ſublimate; The Precipi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:47737:52"/>may be done as well by Acids.</p>
                     </div>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div type="discourse">
                  <head>OTHER <hi>DISCO<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>RSES</hi> UPON Acid <hi>&amp;</hi> Alkali.</head>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>PYROPH.</speaker>
                     <p>THOSE Arguings which we had at our laſt Meeing have almoſt wholly perſuaded me of the Verity of the Hypotheſis of Acid and Alkali: But I muſt
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:47737:53"/>confeſs, dear EUBULUS, that I have been extreamly ſhaken by the Reflections of the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comparable Mr. <hi rend="blackletterType">Boyle</hi> upon theſe Principles, which are lately fallen into my hands, and the Objections which he makes are ſo ſtrong, that it ſeems im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible to bring a ſolution thereof.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>EUB.</speaker>
                     <p>I doubt not but that the Objections which the lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Mr. <hi rend="blackletterType">Boyle</hi> makes againſt Our Hypotheſis have much ſeeming Truth in them; but ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertheleſs, I believe that they may be reſolved with great Eaſe, when one very exactly conſiders what I have ſaid to you concerning the nature of theſe two Principles, and all their force will ſerve to make
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:47737:53"/>the Truth of this Hypotheſis the more conſpicuous.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>PYR.</speaker>
                     <p>Mr. Boyle thinks it ſtrange, That they ſhould ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain all the Qualities of Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies and the other Phoenome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na's of Nature, by this new Syſtem; and, that they attri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute to it an Extent which ought only to be given to Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter and Motion.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>EUB.</speaker>
                     <p>You may eaſily con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude by the ſeveral Phoenome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na's of all ſort of Species which I have explained to you accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to theſe Principles; That it will be eaſy to Explain all thoſe which they ſhall be able to prefer: and I do not ſee Why the Extent that is given to this Hypotheſis, ought to be diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent from that of Matter and
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:47737:54"/>Motion, ſince that in it ſelf is found the Exiſtence of the Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter and Cauſe of Motion.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>PYR,</speaker>
                     <p>Our illuſtrious Engliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man pretends, That they have not made Experiments enough, nor ſufficient Inductions to prove, That Acid and Alkali are to be found in all Bodies, and in all the ſenſible Parts of Mixts; and, That they ought not to conclude, that theſe Two Salts are to be found therein, becauſe ſuch or ſuch Effects are the Emanations of theſe Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples; as for Example, When the Patrons of Acid and Alkali ſee Aqua Fort. or Spirit of Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter diſſolve Filings of Copper, they conclude thereupon, That the Diſſolvant which is Acid, meets, in thoſe filings of Cop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per,
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:47737:54"/>with an Alkali upon which it works: Whereas they do not take Notice, That a well deflegm'd Spirit of Urine, which in their Hypotheſis is a Vola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tile Alkali, diſſolved in a little Flegm, do's diſſolve filings of Copper as readily, and much more naturally than Aqua Fort. doth.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>EUB.</speaker>
                     <p>I believe you have ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiently proved by thoſe Expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riments which I brought you, That there is Acid and Alkali in all parts of Mixts. It is moſt eaſy to ſeparate theſe Two Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples from Animals, Vegeta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles and the moſt part of Mine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rals; but as for Metals, Theſe Principles are therein ſo ſtrict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly united one with the other, That it is almoſt Impoſſible to
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:47737:55"/>diſ-unite them: Nevertheleſs, we ſee therein the ſame Effects as we know are produced in other Bodies by Acid and Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kali, and therefore, we have good ground to believe, That theſe principles are alſo to be met with therein, and, That the ſame effects are produced by the ſame Cauſes. Thus, when we ſee Spirit of Niter and the volatile ſpirit of ſal Armo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niack diſſolve filings of Cop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, we conclude, That there is Acid and Alkali in thoſe fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings, and, That the Acid ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of Niter acts on the Alkali which it finds therein; and the ſharp ſpirit of ſal Armoniack on its Acid: for, 'tis a ſure Maxim That Acid ſpirits never act nor ferment but with Alkali's: and
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:47737:55"/>Alkali's, on the contrary, never act upon any other Bodies but Acids: and thus Mr. Boyle's Objection is of no force, ſeeing Spirit of Niter and Spirit of ſal Armoniack meet in the filings of Copper with different Parts upon which they act different<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and they act not any other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe on the ſame ſubject.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>PYR.</speaker>
                     <p>He continues his Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jections by an Experiment like the former: He ſaies, That in the Solution which is made of Iron by Acid Spirits, they are wont to attribute this Effect to the Acidity, of the Liquor which diſſolved it, although Iron is diſſolv'd redily enough, and alſo in the Cold too, in ſharp Spirits.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>EUB.</speaker>
                     <p>This Objection is as eaſily reſolved as the former:
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:47737:56"/>for there is found in Iron, as there is in Copper, Acid and Alkali; The Spirit of Niter acts on its Alkali, and the Spirit of ſal Armoniack on its Sulphur or Acid, and 'tis ſufficient that the one or other of theſe Two Liquors act upon the Alka<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>li or Acid of the Iron to make the Metal change its Form: as for the reſt, it is ſufficiently eaſy to know, That there are Acid and Alkali in Iron by this, That Iron caſt into Cream hinders that the Butter cannot be made, in as much as it char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges it ſelf with the Acid which ought to make the Coagulati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: and there are none but Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kalies which have the Privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge to produce this Effect: Acids aſſiſting to make this Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>agulation,
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:47737:56"/>as Country-women obſerve; Therefore conſequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly there may be Alkali in Iron. We ſee likewiſe by another fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliar Experiment, That there is Acid in Iron, for, if one puts a bit of iron into Sauce, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in there is ſome Gall, as in that of a Carp, the Gall of which one has broke; all the Volatile Alkali which cauſes the bitter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of the Gall joins it ſelf to the Iron and the Sauce re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mains ſweet: How ſhould this be, that this Volatile Alkali doth join it ſelf to the Iron, if there was not Acid in the Iron, ſeeing Alkali cannot produce ſuch an Effect; it follows there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, That there is Acid in Iron.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>PYR.</speaker>
                     <p>He afterwards de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:47737:57"/>the Reaſon, Why Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cury, (which diſſolves Gold ſo readily, it being a hard and ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lid Body, and reduces it into an Amalgama) acts not at all upon filings of Iron, though this is a Metal ſo open that Liquors weak enough work upon it.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>EUB.</speaker>
                     <p>Two things contribute to this Effect: The firſt is, That there is a great deal more Sulphur in Gold than in Iron, and conſequently, Mercury (which abounds in Alkali) can rather work on Gold than on Iron: The ſecond is, That the Sulphur of Iron is intangled in a great quantity of Earth which hinders the Action of the Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cury which has not parts ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciently subtile nor ſufficiently
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:47737:57"/>penetrating to diſ-intantangle it, as the Spirits of Niter and ſal Armoniack do, whoſe parts are ſo thin and ſo agitated that they diſ-intangle the parts of the Iron one from the other, and makes a Diſ-union of its Sulphur and Alkali: it is not ſo of Gold, whoſe Sulphur is only intangled in its Mercury, and, which hath only a very little Earth, which is not ſtrong enough to intangle the parts of the Sulphur and Mercury of Gold.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>PYR.</speaker>
                     <p>The ſame thing hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pens, which he purſues to the ſame End: In the Precipitati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on which is made of Corals and Peals diſſolved in diſtilled Vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>egar with Oil of Tartar made per deliquium: Chymiſts attri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:47737:58"/>this Precipitation to the Alkali of Tartar, which abſorbs the Acid ſpirits of the Diſſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant, and nevertheleſs we ſee That Acids precipitate them as well as Alkali's.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>EUB.</speaker>
                     <p>I do not wonder, That Acids precipitate equally with Alkali's, Corals and Pearls diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved in diſtilled Vinegar: Yet that does not at all deſtroy the Reaſon, That they are wont to render when it is made with Alkali's: for, there are, as you know, Two ſorts of Diſſolutions in Nature, either an Acid diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolves an Alkali, or elſe an Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kali diſſolves an Acid: if it is an Alkali which holds an Acid in Diſſolution, the Precipitati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on cannot be made but by an Acid, for then the Alkali which
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:47737:58"/>held it in Diſſolution quits it to join it ſelf to the new Acid that is caſt thereto: If, on the contrary, 'tis an Acid which holds an Alkali in Diſſolution, either the Alkali diſſolved by this Acid is mixed intimately with its diſſolvant, in ſuch manner that the diſſolvant fills exactly all the pores of the diſſolved body, as it happens in Vitriol of Mars; or, the diſſolvant do's not penetrate the Body but ſuperficially, and do's not throughly fill the pores thereof, as we obſerve in Mercury diſſolv'd in Aqua fort. and in Coral and Pearls diſſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved in diſtilled Vinegar: If it happens that the Acid ſpirit penetrates intimately the Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to which it is joined, and that
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:47737:59"/>thoſe points be of the ſame fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gure and groſsneſs, as the Pores of that Body, the Precipitation cannot be made but by an Alka<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>li which charges it ſelf with the Acid which held that Body in diſſolution, and makes it at that inſtant to quit its hold: The which Acids cannot do, becauſe that not finding therein any Vacuity they cannot work up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on it. If the Diſſolvant is not mingled per minima with the diſſolved Bodys, an their points are not of a figure proportiona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to thoſe of the pores of the Body, the Precipitation there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of may be made by Acids and Alkali's: by Alkali's after the ſame manner as I told you but now: and, by Acids becauſe the points of theſe Acids work
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:47737:59"/>upon thoſe of the Diſſolvant, cauſing them to quit their hold: for, the Body being no longer agitated nor detained by thoſe points, it falls by its own weight to the bottom of the Veſſel which contains it. Thus when Oil of Tartar precipitates Corals and Pearls diſſolved in diſtilled Vinegar, they have Reaſon to ſay, that this Preci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitation is done, Becauſe the Alkali of Tartar has blunted and charged it ſelf with the points of the diſtilled Vinegar which held the Coral and Pearls in Diſſolution, altho Acids pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipitate alſo this Diſſolution.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>PYR.</speaker>
                     <p>Our Author ſaith, Chapter the Third, That the Admirers of Acid and Alkali ſeem to have aſſign'd, arbitrari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:47737:60"/>certain Extents and Employ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments to each of theſe Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples: as for Example, That an Acid doth, in quality of an A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cid, ſuch and ſuch Operations, and the Alkali's in their quality the like alſo: and, That from thence depends all the Phaeno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mena's of Nature; and, That they ought not to promote, in publiſhing, Propoſitions of this Importance, without good and ſufficient Proofs thereof.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>EUB.</speaker>
                     <p>Does not Experience teach us, That Acids, of what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoev<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>r Nature they be, coagu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late Blood, Milk, &amp;c. That they ferment with all Alkali's, and never with other Acids: That they conſtitute the Eſſence of all Bodies<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> that they are the pointed Bodies which fills up
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:47737:60"/>the Vacuities of Alkali's, and which are the abſolute Maſters thereof; That Alkali's, on the contrary, diſſolve Blood and Milk coagulated by Acids: That they hinder them alſo from being coagulated; and, that their parts are not diſ-united one from the other: For Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample ſake, If one mingle ſom volatile Spirit of Sal Armoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ack with new Milk, or with Blood ſo ſoon as it comes out of the Vein, it conſerves them in their Conſiſtence for a great while, and hinders them from being corrupted: Alka<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>li's whiten Linnen and Stuffs; they ferment well all Acids and never with other Alkali's: Theſe are the little Bodies full of holes and wholly vacuous:
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:47737:61"/>in a word, They precipitate Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triol of Mars diſſolv'd in Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, which Salts nor Acids can never precipitate: You thus ſee plainly, That they aſſign not in vain, theſe nor ſeveral other Effects to Acid's and Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kali's, ſeeing Experience teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth you, That they are alwaies and at all times the Cauſe there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>PYR.</speaker>
                     <p>He affirms alſo, That the Diviſion of Salts into Acid and Alkali is purely arbitrary, and, That they may divide them otherwiſe: Acids and Alkali's having not only in a great many things ſome agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: but alſo ſalts of one and the ſame Denomination being viſibly different in ſeveral chief points: as Alkali's, whereof
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:47737:61"/>ſome are fixed, others volatile; and ſome thereof give a Preci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitation of corroſive Sublimate diſſolved in water of a tawny colour, as ſalt of Tartar; others a white colour, as ſpirit of U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rine, Harts-horn, &amp;c. Finally, ſome act very ſlowly on filings of Copper, as Oil of Tartar made per deliquium, and others diſſolve it with readineſs, as ſpirit of Urine, &amp;c. he adds alſo, That there is no leſs Diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence between Acids: ſome diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolve Bodies which others can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not diſſolve, as Aqua Fortis which diſſolves Silver, Mercu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, &amp;c. and touches not Gold: and, as Aqua Regis which diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolves Gold, and touches nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Silver nor the other Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tals: Spirit of Vinegar well de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flegm'd
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:47737:62"/>diſſolves Lead in the Cold, and reduces it into mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nute parts, which Spirit of common Salt cannot do: and he concludes this Chap demanding whether Acid and Alkali have the Simplicity that a Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pher requires in Principles? and in Smiling at the Definition that they are Wont to give, That Acid is an Enemy to Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kali, and Alkali to Acid.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>EUB.</speaker>
                     <p>The Diviſion of ſimple Salts into Acid and Alkali is as Juſt and Exact as can be wiſh'd; Acids and Alkali's having not any agreement in Virtue and Property, and the one never produceth the Effects of the other: as Mr. Boyle would have it: as for Example, Alka<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>li's are Bodies vacuous and full
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:47737:62"/>of holes, which precipitate Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triol of Mars diſſolved in Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, which whiten Linnen and Stuffs; which make a Diſſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Milk and Blood coagala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by Acids. &amp;c. Acids, on the contrary, are pointed Bodys, which fill up the little holes they meet with in Alkali's, which foul Linnen and Stuffs, which coagulate Blood and Milk, &amp;c. in a word, which have not any of the Properties of Alkali's. And, though Salts of one and the ſame Denomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion differ in ſome things, yet nevertheleſs, they all agree in Nature and uſe: for we ſee. That Alkali's, whether fixed or volatile, are Bodys full of holes, That they all precipitate Vitri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ol of Mars: That Acids, on
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:47737:63"/>the contrary, are pointed Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, &amp;c. ſo that when ſome Alkali's precipitate corroſive Sublimate diſſolved in water, into a tawny coloured Powder, and ſome others into a white powder, that does not prove, That they have a different Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture one from the other, but that comes from the Diverſity of their Pores, ſome having them more conformable to the Acid which had ſublimed the Mercury and others leſs, and they blunt after this manner more or leſs the points of thoſe Acids, whence comes the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſity of colours of the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipitate: It is not alſo the Diverſity of Natures that makes that Volatile Alkali's diſſolves Copper more rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:47737:63"/>than fixed Alkali's do: but only the greater agitation of their parts: all Acids work on Silver and the other Metals, but more or leſs, according to the greater or leſſer Relation their points have with the pores of thoſe Metals: Theſe Acids never work on Gold which cannot be diſſolved but by ſalt Menſtruums, as I have ſaid elſe-where. And, whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever Mr. Boyle ſays of ſpirit of Salt, which he cites for a moſt powerful Acid, is Salt, and not a pure Acid, notwithſtanding the Acid ſeems to predominate therein: and, That is the Reaſon why ſpirit of Salt works neither on ſilver nor the other Metals.</p>
                     <p>Theſe two Salts have the
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:47737:64"/>Simplicity that a Philoſopher requires in Principles, becauſe they are compoſed of Particles of one and the ſame Nature, and can never be reſolv'd into any other Subſtances. In reſpect of the Definition which Mr. Boyle relates of Acid and Alkali, he has Reaſon to blame it, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he doth in no wiſe ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain the Nature of theſe Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples, no more than if one ſhould ſay, That that which diſſolves a Body diſſolvable by an Acid, ought to be an Acid: &amp;, That all which precipitates a body diſſolv'd by an Acid, ought to be an Alkali: but Mr. Boyle cannot ſay the ſame thing of the Definition which I have al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready ſo many times repeated concerning Acid and, Alkali:
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:47737:64"/>That the Acid is a Salt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed of ſmall pointed parts which ferment with Alkali's &amp; makes the Eſſence of all Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies: The Alkali, on the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary, is a vacuous Salt which ferments with Acids, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipitates Vitriol of Mars diſſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved in water. This Definiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on explains clearly their Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, Kind and Difference; for, theſe two Principles agree in that they are Salts; and they differ in that one of them is pointed, and the other porous and unequal, and that one fills the Pores of the other, and is its abſolute Maſter.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>PYR.</speaker>
                     <p>This Famous Engliſh-Man will not allow, <note place="margin">Chap. 4.</note> That the Fermentation or Heat and Ebu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lition which is cauſed when
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:47737:65"/>theſe Two Salts are mingled to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, is a ſure Token to know Acid and Alkali: For, he pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tends, That theſe Effects depend principally on the Mechanick Diſpoſition and Conſtruction of Parts; and, That 'tis ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent to produce heat when the parts of a Body are agitated with vehemence on all ſides: and, for the Ebulition, That the Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies which are mingled inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept the parts of the air, or the warm Vapours in the time that they are excited; and, That there happens often in this mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>xture Heat without Ebulition, and Ebulition without Heat: He relates ſome Experiments of both: For, he ſaith, When Oil of Vitriol, which is a pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erful Acid; or, Salt of Tartar,
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:47737:65"/>which is a powerful Alkali, are mingled with Water which is neither Acid nor Alkali; There is at that time a conſiderable heat excited, without any Ebu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lition: and, That on the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary, in the Mixture which is made of ſpirit of verdigriſs, made per ſe, which is an Acid, with ſalt of Tartar: there is made a great Ebulition and groſs Froth without any re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>markable heat.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>EUB.</speaker>
                     <p>It is very true, That the Heat and Ebulition which happens in Fermentation de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pends upon the Mechanick diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition and Conſtruction of the parts of Bodys which are Fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented: But this Conſtruction or Diſpoſition likewiſe depends wholly upon the different na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:47737:66"/>of Acids and Alkali's, and their divers mixtures one with the other, as I have already cauſed you to obſerve, where I ſpoke of Fermentation and its Differences, which would be needleſs here to repeat: as for the oil of Vitriol and Salt of Tartar which heat water when they are diſſolved therein; you ſhall obſerve, That there is in Oil of vitriol, a metallick part of Iron or Copper according to the Nature of the Vitriol which was elevated in the Diſtillati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on by the Acid of that Salt, as Experience ſufficiently teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth us: This oil coming to be diſſolved in the water, there is then made a ſeparation of the Metallick part from the Acid, which had elevated it; and an
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:47737:66"/>action of that Acid upon the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kali of the water; which is powerful enough, ſince it har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dens red hot Iron, and hinders it from going into ſcoria's, when it is ſquenched therein, for, there is none but Alkali's which can produce this effect: then there is made on all ſides an agitation of their parts, with ſufficient Vehemence, whence comes the heat which happens in this mixture. In regard of that which reſults from the mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>xture of ſalt of Tartar with wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, you ſhall underſtand that ſalt of Tartar does hot heat wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, but when it is too much or too little calcined: when it is too much calcined, it is char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged with an Acid from the fire, which coming to be diſſolved
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:47737:67"/>in water, it ſeparates it ſelf from the Alkali of the Tartar, and acts upon that of the water, and cauſes, as I have ſaid but now, the heat in the water: and when the Tartar is not ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently calcined, it retains ſome of its own Acid, and becomes a little near the nature of Calx vive, which cauſes it to fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in water: but when this Salt is neither too much nor too little calcined, it diſſolves ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply in water without cauſing therein any Heat, as all pure Alkali's do.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>PYR.</speaker>
                     <p>He afterwards comes to ſpeak of the Taſt, which he ſaies, is as the Touch-ſtone to know Acids and Alkali's: he ſaith thereupon, That there are a great many mixts, in which
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:47737:67"/>the Taſt can ſo little diſcern which of thoſe two Principles predominate therein, that one cannot ſuſpect that there is in thoſe two Bodys the leaſt part of thoſe Two Salts, as in Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, Rubys, Gold, Silver, &amp;c. That there are alſo ſeveral Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dys which abound in Acid and Alkali Salts, yet have no taſt at all, or, which have one altogether different from that which the Chymiſts attribute to their Principles, as Venice Glaſs, which is inſipid on the Tongue, though it is almoſt no other thing but fixt Alkali; and as Criſtals of Silver and Lead made with aqua fortis, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of the firſt has an extream Bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terneſs, and the laſt, the ſweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of Sugar; neither of which
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:47737:68"/>retain any thing of Acid of the aq. Fort. which did diſſolve thoſe Metals.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>EUB.</speaker>
                     <p>By the Taſte we can only know pure Acids and Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kalis, as the Spirits of Sulphur, Niter, &amp;c. which are taken Notice of by their acidity: and as the volatile Alkali's of Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, Harts-horn, and fixed Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kali's as lixivial. Salts, which are known by their great a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crimony: as ſoon as theſe two Salts are mixt together they produce different Savours ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the divers Mixture and particular figure of their Parts: It happens alſo very of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten that a body which experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence teacheth us a acid, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing mingled with a Body which experience makes us know
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:47737:68"/>to be an Alkali, they being in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſipid: as for Example, When four parts of Cream of Tartar diſſolved in Water: in which may be manifeſtly ſeen, that the Acid predominates, is mingled with two parts of Salt of Tartar diſſolved alſo in water, there is made as ſoon as they come together a Fermentation ſufficiently violent, from which afterwards is obtained, by Cri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtallization, a ſalt which is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together inſipid. You ſee by this Experiment, That though a Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy be inſipid, nevertheleſs one may not conclude, That it c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>n<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains neither Acid nor Alk<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>li<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> therein.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>PYR.</speaker>
                     <p>Mr. Boyle pretends is the fifth Chapter, That the Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>potheſis of Acid and Alkali is
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:47737:69"/>neither Neceſſary nor Uſeful to explain that which happens to qualitys; Whereof ſome are produced, others deſtroy'd or altered; it not appearing, Th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>t theſe two Principles contribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in any wiſe thereto; as when Water is changed by the force of Beating into Froth, which hath ſome Conſiſtence: or, as when Coral which is red and tranſparent, is changed in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a white and opacous Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, without doing any other thing thereto than reducing it into a Powder ſufficiently ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>til to paſs through a fine Searce.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>EUB.</speaker>
                     <p>The Froth which is formed on water by Beating comes only from the agitation of its parts, and as there are a
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:47737:69"/>great many Alkali parts, and alſo ſome Acid parts, and a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle Earth to be met with in wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, it is certain, That theſe Principles contribute to the Production of this Quality. It ſhould be needful that Mr Boyle prove, That there is no Acid nor Alkali in water, to conclude That Acid and Alkali do not contribute in any wiſe to the production of this new Quality; which is impoſſible to be done: as for the Coral, which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes white and opacous when it is reduced into an Impalpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Powder: I ſhall tell you, That the moſt part of Bodies are deſtroy'd by Trituration, and entirely change their Nature, and thoſe alſo which are harder and ſolider: and if we may be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:47737:70"/>ſome, of the Renouned Chymiſts of our Age, as the famous Langelot, Olaus; Bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rychius, Schroder, &amp;c. Leaf-Gold is deſtroyed in ſuch wiſe by a long Trituration, that it is impoſſible to make it retake the form of Gold, whatſoever artifice you uſe: ſo that it is not ſtrange, That Coral which is red and tranſparent, ſhould become white and opacous, when it is reduced to an impal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable powder, becauſe that in the Trituration which is made thereof, its parts are diſ-united in ſuch wiſe one from the other, and are in ſo great a confuſion, that they can no longer keep their natural colour, either be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they do no longer reflect the light as they did reflect it
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:47737:70"/>before; or, becauſe they do not make the ſame. Impreſſion on the aier: or laſtly, that the, Attoms which go out there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>from are not conditioned as they were: and this colour cannot return to it, except by the force of ſome exteriour a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent its particles retake the ſame place, and the ſame ſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuation as they occupied before the Trituration: as we take notice of it in blew Vitriol, which becomes white when re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced into pouder, and which retakes its natural colour when this powder is diſſolved in wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and afterwards cauſed to criſtallize.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>PYR.</speaker>
                     <p>He proceeds with an Objection like the former; He ſaies, They cannot render a
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:47737:71"/>Reaſon by Acid and Alkali of Gravity, Light, and ſeveral o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Qualities, which are called MANIFEST; and much leſs of thoſe which are called OC<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>CULT: as of the Force of the Loadſtone on Iron, and of Iron on the Loadſtone, as well as ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral other Phaenomena's of the Loadſtone.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>EUB.</speaker>
                     <p>The gravity and levi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of a body depends upon the more or leſs of Vacuity that there is in that body, according to Mr. Boyle's Opinion, in ſuch manner, That a body in which there are feweſt Vacuities, is moſt Weight, as, on the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary, that in which there are more vacuitys, is more light. Now the Moreneſs or Leſsneſs of Vacuities depends upon the
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:47737:71"/>Moreneſs or Leſsneſs of the acid which there is in Bodies: for, when there is a great deal of Acid therein, the Pores of the Alkali are filled therewith; and, when on the contrary, there is but a very little Acid, thoſe Pores remain empty, and conſequently the gravity of a Body depends upon the quanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of Acid that is found therein, and the Levity upon the ſmall<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of the Acid and quantity of Alkali which is found there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in: The abundance of Caput Mort. contributes much to the lightneſs of Bodys, as we obſerve in the Firr-tree which is a ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry light wood, and hath much Earth in it. Light is no other but an agitation of ſmall poin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Bodys which are poured
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:47737:72"/>out in the air, and puts all the parts thereof in Motion: It is of the ſame Nature with fire ſince it produceth the ſame Ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects, and that being re-united in a burning-glaſs, it liquefies Metals and calcines Stones as fire doth, which is Acid, as I have proved elſe-where, and by conſequence Light ought alſo to be an Acid, ſince it hath all the qualities thereof. The Ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects which are attributed to qualities, and are called. OC<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>CULT draw no leſs their Ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginal from Acid, and Alkali than the manifeſt Qualities, which I ſhall ſhew you when I ſpeak of ſome Effects of the Load-ſtone; The moſt conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derable whereof is, That where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by it draweth Iron. You ſhall
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:47737:72"/>take notice therefore, That I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ron is an imperfect Load ſtone, which hath Pores of the ſame figure with thoſe of the Load-ſtone, and which are filled with the ſame Particles as thoſe wherewith the Load-ſtone is fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led. We ſee likewiſe, That I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ron, expoſed to the air a long time, becomes Load-ſtone, ſince it acquires the qualitys thereof, as the Croſſes which are upon Churches, theſe in Succeſſion of time become Load-ſtones, and produce the ſame Effect as the Load-ſtone. You ſhall like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe take notice, That there are a great many more Pores in the Load-ſtone than there is in Iron, and, That the force of the Load-ſtone conſiſts in the ſmall pointed Bodyes that fill
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:47737:73"/>theſe pores; Iron becoming Load-ſtone in the air, furniſheth us with a moſt convincing Proof thereof; for, Experience teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth us, That all porous Bodies are charged in the air, with an Acid of their own nature, as the earth from whence Salt-petar has been drawn, which is there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in charged with a new Salt-pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tar, which is acid, &amp;c. Laſtly, you ſhall obſerve, That there goes out continually from the Loadſtone a multitude of theſe little pointed bodies, and at the ſame time there enters therein<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to others which retake their place, becauſe the air is wholly filled therewith: This being granted, it is ſufficiently eaſy to render a reaſon for the attracti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Iron by the Load-ſtone.
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:47737:73"/>The attoms which go out con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually from the Load-ſtone inſinuate themſelves into the Pores of the Iron and fills them, Theſe Corpuſcles cannot go out from the Load-ſtone, but at the ſame time they agitate the air with violence, this agitated air throws the Iron againſt the Load-ſtone, or the Load-ſtone againſt the Iron, according as the one of theſe Bodies reſiſts it, and after this manner the Load-ſtone attracts Iron, and Iron the Load-ſtone. You ſee plainly, That this Virtue, which did for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly ſilence all the Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phers, is explained by our Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>potheſis, and that, after a man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner ſo natural, that it is eaſy to judge, That all the other Phe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nomena's of the Load-ſtone
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:47737:74"/>ought as certainly to be produ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced according to our Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>PYR.</speaker>
                     <p>Mr. Boyle, in Conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, Makes an Objection, which to me ſeems ſufficiently ſtrong: he demands, How in the Diſſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution of Metals, their Parts are ſuſtained by the Diſſolvant, though the Mettal be in equal bulk nine times heavier than the water; and if it be Gold, nine times heavier than the liquor which hinders it from ſinking, and always a great deal heavier in particular, than the Salts which compoſe the Diſſolvant, can render the water in which they are mingled.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>EUB.</speaker>
                     <p>It is eaſy to compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend how the parts of Metals diſſolved in Acid ſpirits, ſharp
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:47737:74"/>Spirits and ſalt Meſtruums are ſuſtained by theſe Diſſovants: It is becauſe their parts are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually agitated by thoſe of thoſe Liquors whoſe motion is ſufficiently ſtrong, an ſufficient<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly rapid to carry them with them, and to hinder them from precipitating.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>PYR.</speaker>
                     <p>I did not believe, That you were able, without ſeeking ſome other Principles than theſe which you have eſtabliſhed, to ſatisfy the Objections of the il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luſtrious Mr. Boyle: But you raiſed all the Difficulties there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of with ſo much Force, that they have only ſerved to give a greater illuſtration to your Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples, and to ſhew the extent thereof, and their Conformity, to Reaſon and Experience.</p>
                     <pb n="128" facs="tcp:47737:75"/>
                     <p>NOW, ſeeing a Genius ſo delicate, and which knows Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture ſo exactly, as that Learned Man, has not been able to give them any Attaint, I doubt not but day by day they will be confirmed, as we make new Diſcoveries therein; and, that they will remain firm and ſtead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faſt againſt all that can be em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploy'd to ſhake and deſtroy them.</p>
                  </sp>
               </div>
               <div type="reply">
                  <pb n="129" facs="tcp:47737:75"/>
                  <head>A REPLY TO A LETTER OF <hi>Mr.</hi> S. touching the Nature of Acid <hi>&amp;</hi> Alkali.</head>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>SIR,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>NOne can doubt but there is much Honour to be acquired by Publiſhing the New Diſcoveries which are made in Phyſick and Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cine; but, I muſt alſo confeſs, That it is not Advantageous to write, when we are moved thereto only by Envy, to cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:47737:76"/>the Works of others, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out conſidering, Whether the things that we write are indeed what they ſeem to be in the I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>magination. This is the Dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference that there is between the manner whereof Mr. Houp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peville hath faithfully commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicated to us the Obſervations which he had made upon the Corps of a Woman, and that whereof you freely attack him, without being in any wiſe obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged thereto: Yet I am leſs ſurpriſed at it than at your pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding concerning the Facul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of Caen, which you treat after the ſharpeſt and violenteſt manner in the World: which cannot proceed but from a Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit very little inclined to ſpeak well of any one; and all the
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:47737:76"/>abuſes which can be made a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt a Faculty whoſe Reputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is ſo well eſtabliſhed, and hath ſo juſt a Title, cannot but return with Diſgrace upon their Author, ſince no Body will ever balance the Authority of a particular perſon, who aims to be known only by the Faults which he endeavours to diſcover in others, with that of a Society, whoſe Doctrine and Exactneſs have rendred it ſo famous, and which (without ſpeaking of thoſe which adorn their places ſo worthily at pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent) hath produced Men moſt Famous in their time, ſuch as were Cahagneſe, Dalechamp, Schroder and ſeveral other Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous Doctors, whoſe Names will laſt as long as the SCI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ENCE
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:47737:77"/>to which they have applyed themſelves: and all the ill Treatments which Envy and Jealouſy can borrow of Railery and ſuppoſition, will but increaſe the true Eſteem we ought to have for it. Likewiſe there are ſome perſons whoſe Judgments are ſo little confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mable to the Rules of Reaſon, that a man may be eſteem'd by diſpleaſing them. I know not whether the Praiſes which you give to the celebrated Faculty of Montpelier, whereof you call your ſelf Doctor, be not more prejudicial than advanta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geous to it; and the manner by which you Depick'd it, a Slave to the Opinions of the Ancients, and an enemy to the new Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tomick and Chymick Diſcove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries: where you ſay, It can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:47737:77"/>Deceive, nor be Deceived, <note place="margin">Pag 3. 4.</note> becauſe it does not receive any Novelties, if the contrary was not known, it would be thought blind, and incapable to be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lightned by thoſe Lights which the Exactneſs of the Anatomiſts and Works of the Chymiſts of our time have diſcovered to us. I know well, That the Light<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to change Opinions, and the too great Aptneſs to receive Novelties, is a Fault; but not greater than wilfully to retain an old Errour, and refuſe one's Conſent and Belief to a Truth but lately found out. Truth is not of any Age, it is not ſubject to Years, but it is in it ſelf E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal; and 'tis only the Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation we make thereof that is of ſuch a year. A Geogra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pher
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:47737:78"/>could not handſomly deny, That there is a fourth Part of the World, becauſe Pto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomy, Strabo and other antient Geographers did not know it: How fair ſoever the Deſcripti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons be which antient Anatomiſts have made on MAN, yet they have left to us ſome Parts of this Microcoſm to be diſcove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, which tho they be not of any great Extent, nevertheleſs they are of extream Importance for its Conſervation: and our antient Philoſophers have not penetrated ſo deep into rhe Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crets of Nature, but that we have Diſcovered by means of CHIMISTRY many things which were unknown to them. You obſerve ſo little the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>xims for which you praiſe the
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:47737:78"/>Faculty of Montpellier, that without fear to cheat or be cheated, you reaſon by Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples all-together unknown to the Antients: and, you admit ſeveral new Anatomicks and Chimicks, but you turn them lo particularly, that they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come unknown to their own In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venters: and, I know not but the uſe which you make there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of will rather ſerve to Deſtroy then to Eſtabliſh them.</p>
                  <p>The manner by which you explain Nutrition, Renders us not much more knowing; You tell us, <note place="margin">pag. 79, &amp; 107.</note> The Chyle is made in the Stomach, without teaching us the manner thereof; That it falls afterwards into the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtins, where it is fermented with the Bile and ſplenetick
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:47737:79"/>Juice without explaining to us the Cauſe of this Fermentation: and you go on with an evident falſe ſuppoſition, That it is car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryed to the Liver by the Vena Porta; after, having paſſed through the Tunicks of the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtines, to acquire therein the form of Blood. For, to diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver the Cauſe and Means of theſe Operations, it muſt be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved, That there is an Acid Liquor in the Stomach, which produceth them therein; Whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther this Liquor be brought thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by the extremities of the Arteries which terminate there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to; or elſe it is the remains of the Aliments which grow ſour by abiding there, and which ſerve as Leven to thoſe that are taken afterwards, as we obſerve
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:47737:79"/>that Dough grows ſour by age, and then it can ferment a great quantity of new. The exiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of this Liquor needs not be doubted of, nor that it is a powerful diſſolvant: The Bones which we find half digeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in the Stomachs of Dogs, and the Copper which we find half corroded and half diſſolved in the Stomachs of Oſtriges and Drakes, are ſufficient Teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies thereof.</p>
                  <p>And we may perceive that this Acid Liquor was not un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>known to the incomparable Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocrates, when he ſaith in the firſt Aphoriſm of the ſixth Sec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, <hi>In longis laevitatibus Inteſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norum ſi rectus Acidus ſuperveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>at, bonum,</hi> In long Looſneſſes of the Inteſtines, if acid Belch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:47737:80"/>ſupervene, it is good, for 'tis then that this Liquor begins to be renewed and to execute its functions. When the Sto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mach is empty and this Liquor is fallen thereinto, in a ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent large quantity, or elſe (if you pleaſe) the Ferment is ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciently exalted, it excites Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, for then it ſtrikes the ſupe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rior Orifice of the Stomach, which is wholy nervous, and of a moſt delicate Senſe, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duceth in us different Appetites according to the particular Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture and different Figure of its Particles; whence it comes, That we do digeſt more eaſily thoſe aliments to which our ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petite excites us, becauſe they have much conformity with that Acid. This Liquor ſerves
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:47737:80"/>not only to excite Hunger, but alſo to diſſolve the Aliments which we take, and to convert them into Chyle: for, after the Aliments have been prepared in the Mouth by maſtication, and by the mixture of the Spittle, they are caſt by the Tongue in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Oeſophage, and fall at the ſame time into the Stomach, as well by their own weight as by the impulſion of the Muſcles of the Oeſophage, the acid li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quor of the Stomach is immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately mingled with them, ſcat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tering the parts thereof from the other, and bruiſes them, and attenuates them, and by the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinual agitation and motion which it makes thereof, it cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes them entirely to change their Nature; and, according to the relation that this liquor has with
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:47737:81"/>the aliments which we take; the Chylification is made more or leſs perfect, and in more or leſs time. The Stomach being continually preſſed by the Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phragma in the time of Reſpira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, the Chyle falls inſenſibly into the Inteſtines, where it is confounded with the Bile and pancreick Juice, and then there is made a Fermentation of the Chyle with theſe two Liquors, during which time, the more ſubtile parts, and conſequently the more proper to nouriſh the animal, are ſtrained, and paſs through the Tunicks of the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtines, and the groſſer parts are caſt out backwards by the anus, as well by their own weight, as by the periſtatick Motion of the Inteſtines. Sylvi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:47737:81"/>de le Boe, Graaf, Suale, &amp;c. have attributed the cauſe of this Fermentation of the Chyle with the Byle and pancreick Juice to the acidity of the pancreick Juice, but experience hath taught our more curious Anato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſts. That this Juice is not in any wiſe acid, but altogether incipid, and therefore, That can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be the cauſe of this Fermen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation; and to diſcover the true Cauſe thereof, it muſt be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved. That when the Chyle falls from the Stomack into the Inteſtines, it is of an acid-ſalt taſte, becauſe of the Mixture of the Acid of the Spittle and of the acid Liquor of the Sto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mach with the volatile Alkali of the Aliments; for, as I have ſhewed in my foregoing Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe,
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:47737:82"/>that Acid-Salt Bodies are compoſed of a Mixture of Acid with Alkali. This Taſte is found manifeſtly in the Chyle; and 'tis, in other Caſes, a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant Maxim, That Acid-Salt Bodyes being mixed with ſome Alkali, and diſſolved in ſome Menſtruum (for Salts act not except diſſolved) are ferment<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, as Vitriol of Mars doth, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing diſſolved in water, with Oil of Tartar made per deliquium. The Chyle then being an acid-Salt, and the Bile abounding in volatile Alkali, they are fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented aſſoon as they come to be diſſolved by the pancreick Juice. This Fermentation can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be made but at the ſame there is made a Precipitation of the Faeces, and the more ſubtile
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:47737:82"/>parts paſs into the lacteal Veins, and not into the Vena porta, and from thence into the Liver, as you ſuppoſe: for, if the Bran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches of the Vena porta, in the time of the Diſtribution of the Chyle, be tyed, they are found only filled with Blood, and if they be ſeparated with the Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver from the Inteſtines, there is likewiſe not loſt one drop of Chyle, but it is carryed conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nually from the Inteſtines into the lacteal Veins, from theſe veins into the two Receivers of Pequet, and then into the tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rachick Pipe, where it is ming<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led with the Lympha which is diſcharged thereinto from the inferiour parts, and aſcending all a-long by this pipe, it is diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gorged into the left ſubclavial
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:47737:83"/>Vein, where it is confounded with the Blood; and, continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing its way it falls into the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcending Vena Cava, where it is ſtill mingled with the Blood that it contains, and the Lym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pha which flows thereto from the ſuperiour parts; it enters laſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly into the Heart, where it is ſubtilized, and begins to be chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged into Blood, and by circula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting ſeveral times from the Heart into the arteries, from the arteries into the Veins, and from the veins into the Heart again, it is rendred proper to nouriſh the animal; the ſubtiler parts whereof penetrating as va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pours thro' the Tunicks of the arteries and joining and uniting themſelves to the Parts, nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh and augment them, and the
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:47737:83"/>reſt is drained into the Liver, Reins, Pancrea's, &amp;c. and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Laws of Circu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation repaſſes into the Veins, and from the Veins into the Heart, where it is refurniſhed with Spirits by the means of a Ferment, which is contained in its Ventricles, and by the Mix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of the Air, which inſinu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ates it ſelf through the Lungs into the Heart.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I</hi> could prove by many Expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riments, That the pancreick Juice comes not from the Spleen to the Pancrea's,<note place="margin">Pag. 79.</note> as you pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend: But, as the thing is of it ſelf, ſufficiently clear, and that we need but obſerve the ſtructure of theſe two Viſce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra's, and the communication that they have one with the
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:47737:84"/>other to convince you thereof:</p>
                  <p>It will be ſufficient to cauſe you to take Notice of that which modern Anatomiſts have ſeveral times experimented, That after the Spleen hath been taken from Dogs, the Wound being conſolidated, theſe Dogs have been as well as if they ſtill had their Spleen, and we draw a pancreick Juice therefrom, altogether like that which we ordinarily draw. Wherefore, if the Spleen did communicate this Juice to the Pancrea's, it is certain, That theſe Dogs, whoſe Spleen was cut out, would languiſh, and Nutrition would no longer be perfectly made, becauſe the Chyle is not fermented with the Bile, for want of the Pan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creick Juice, which is the Men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruum
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:47737:84"/>that diſſolves theſe two Bodyes, and which puts them in action: there would alſo be no longer any ſecretion of the Cream of the Chyle from the Excrements, and we could not be able to draw a Pancreick Juice from theſe Animals, for the Cauſe being remov'd, there is no longer any Effect, <hi>ſublata Cauſa, tollitur Effectus.</hi> The pan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creick Juice comes not then from the Spleen to the Pancrea's but is a Liquor which is ſtrained in the Pancrea's as the Serocity in the Reins.</p>
                  <p>It is not a vain Fancy, as you go on, to believe, <note place="margin">Pag. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>3</note> That the Lym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pha is a Serocity which is ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated from the Blood, and from the nervous Juice in the Glands: if you had examined the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:47737:85"/>of the Glans, and the Veſſels which terminate there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, you would judge otherwiſe thereof: You would ſee, that the Glands are as ſo many ſtrai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, through which the Sero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity is ſtrained, and there ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minates thereto four Sorts of Veſſels, namely Nerves, Arte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, Veins, and the Lympha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick, Veſſels; the Arteries car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Blood thereto, which the Veins re-carry to the Heart, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Laws of Circula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, the Nerves carry the ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mal Spirits or nervous Juice thereto, and the Lymphatick Veſſels draw thereto the Lym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pha, and is diſcharged thereof, as I have already ſaid, into the thorachick Pipe, and into the deſcending Vena cava: You
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:47737:85"/>ſee from hence, That ſince the Glands have no other Veſſels which adminiſter thereto but Nerves and Arteries, it neceaſſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily follows, That the Lympha is a Serocity which is ſeparated from the Blood, and from the nervous Juice in the Glands.</p>
                  <p>You ſay, There is neither A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cid nor Alkali in the Seed, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe that being the Decidu of [or that which is fallen off from] all the Body, <note place="margin">Pag. 109.</note> and the Recidu of the laſt Aliment, it ſuffers nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the one nor the other: ſince they have been ſeparated there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>from in the firſt Concoction of the Aliment, and are not to be ound in the ſecond, which is the Haematoſe, and yet leſs in the Third, which is the aſſimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation,
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:47737:86"/>or Nutrition of Parts.</p>
                  <p>You add, That if there were Acid and Alkali in the Seed, it would be deſtroy'd by the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinual Ebbulition and Fermenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion which is made thereof. It is to be admired that you can be of this Opinion, ſeeing ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Doctrine which you would eſtabliſh, you can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not deny, but the ſeed hath the ſame Principles, as, Fleſh, Blood, Bones, Horns, and other parts of Animals, and 'tis otherwiſe indi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſputable, That Meat, Blood and Milk which grow ſour when they corrupt, contain Acid and the Volatile Alkali's which are drawn in abundance therefrom, are Proofs no leſs certain, That there is an Alkali therein; whence it follows, That theſe
<pb n="151" facs="tcp:47737:86"/>two Salts are alſo to be found in the Seed, ſince according to what you affirm, It is only the Reſidue of the laſt Aliment of of thoſe parts: as for the Obje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction which you make, That if there were Acid and Alkali in the Seed, it would be corrupt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed becauſe of the continual Fermentation which is made theteof: You ſhall alſo ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve, That theſe two Salts ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver act, except they be diſſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved or excited by ſome exter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Agent, as Heat, or by the mixture of ſome other Body: as it happens, when the Seed of the Male and that of the Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>male come to be mingled toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and to be heated in the Womb, for then all their parts are put into Motion, and there
<pb n="152" facs="tcp:47737:87"/>is made a Patern or rough draught of all thoſe of the Foe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus: the more ſubtile parts of the ſeed retire themſelves to the Center, and ſcatter to the Circumference thoſe which their groſsneſs or figure render leſs proper for motion, from which are produced the Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>branes which environ the Foe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus; and the more ſubtile parts continue their motion in the middle, diſ-intangling them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves from thoſe whoſe figure is not proportionable to theirs, and uniting themſelves to thoſe which are with them confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mable; and ſo thoſe which are Decidued [or fallen] from the Brain, or more properly thoſe which are found proper to form the Brain, unite together and
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:47737:87"/>produce the Brain. Thoſe which ought to form the Heart, unite together and form the Heart, and ſo of all the other parts: and when it happens that the Man's Seed overpow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers that of the Woman's, there is formed a Man; as there is formed a Woman, when that of the Woman's is ſtronger than the Mans: and we may believe that there may be an Herma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phrodite when both Seeds meet together in a perfect Equality.</p>
                  <p>Where you begin to treat of Acid and Alkali; you tell us, You can hardly give your Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion thereof, <note place="margin">Pag 89.</note> becauſe it is diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cult to declate it upon a mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter which ('till now) is unde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termined: yet nevertheleſs you,
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:47737:88"/>as it ſeems, decide it ſo abſolute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, as if it were the moſt known and determined Truth in the World.</p>
                  <p>You pretend, that Acid is a principle of Death, and the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kali a principle of Life, <note place="margin">Pag 96.</note> that is to ſay, That Acids are the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyers of Bodies, and Alkali's, on the contrary, the Authors of their Conſtruction. For to make the Probability of this Maxim diſappear, one needs only to make reflection upon what I have ſpoken thereof in my Diſcourſes upon Acid and Alkali, where I have ſpoke of the Regeneration of compound Mineral Salts, and the Eſſenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al Salts of Plants: for, it is moſt certain, That Acids are not the deſtroyers of Bodyes,
<pb n="155" facs="tcp:47737:88"/>nor Alkali's their Authors, ſince all Alkali's are determined by Acids, to make Bodyes of the ſame Nature with thoſe from which they were drawn: and if it happens ſometimes, That Acids deſtroy ſome Bodies, as common Sulphur doth Iron, that happens becauſe there is little Alkali to be found in thoſe Bodyes, and the Acid being in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tangled therein, in a great deal of Earth, it may eaſily be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>intangled therefrom by another Acid, the which intirely de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroys the Compoſition, but that happens not in thoſe Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyes where the Acid is fixed, and united intimately with its Alkali, as it is in Gold, Silver, &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>You bring us Tartar of Wine
<pb n="156" facs="tcp:47737:89"/>for the firſt of all Acids, and you prove it after ſo convincing a manner, <note place="margin">
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>g 93.</note> That the ſame Reaſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing may be applyed in all its force to all the other Tartars of Vegetables. It is the firſt, ſay you, in its generation and Action: it is the firſt in its ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration, becauſe it is produc'd ſuch by nature, for it is in Grapes together with the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kali of wine, and ſo long as Nature governs them they have not any motion of altera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion one againſt the other, &amp;c. but as ſoon as Nature doth ceaſe to govern them, they ferment themſelves one with the other into Wine, &amp;c. May not the ſame thing be ſaid of all the other Vegetables? They have all their Acid and Alkali pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced
<pb n="157" facs="tcp:47737:89"/>ſuch by Nature, they are not diſ-united but when Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture ceaſes to govern them, they are fermented in their Juices, as the Alkali and Acid of Grapes are in Wine.</p>
                  <p>You are not contented to aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure us. That Tartar is the firſt of Acids, but alſo, That its Acid conſiſts in its Salt, and, That that which is diſtilled there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>from, is the Volatile Alkali of Wine, which this Acid had ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſorbed. The Anatomy of Tar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tar will perhaps make you be of another Opinion, for there is drawn therefrom firſt a Flegm by Diſtillation; Secondly, an Acid Spirit, which ferments with all Alkali's: Thirdly, a ſtinking Oil, and laſtly, a fixed Salt, which is ſeparated from
<pb n="158" facs="tcp:47737:90"/>its Caput Mort. by Lixiviation, which ferments with all Acids, and precipitates Vitriol of Mars diſſolved in Water.</p>
                  <p>The Acid ſpirit of Tartar is of the ſame Nature with that of Vinegar, as may be ſeen by this Experiment.</p>
                  <p>℞ ſome Salt of Tartar, and pour thereupon good Vinegar, until it will take in no more, and there will be made a rege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerated Tartar like to that of Wine, whoſe ſourneſs is gone: You may perceive then by this, That that Spirit which is drawn from Tartar, is not the volatile Alkali of Wine, which the Tar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tar had abſorbed, as you teach us; but it is, on the contrary, the volatile Acid of Wine, which cauſeth it in time to degene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate
<pb n="159" facs="tcp:47737:90"/>into Vinegar. The black and ſtinking Oil which went forth after the Flegm and Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, is an enveloped Acid, as are all the Oils of Vegetables. In a word, The Salt that is drawn from Tartar is as powerful an Alkali as any there is in Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, which, as I ſaid even now, ferments with all Acids', and does precipitate Vitriol of Mars diſſolved in Water.</p>
                  <p>It ſeems alſo you have ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledged this Truth, when you ſaid, That Oil of Tar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tar made <hi>per deliquium</hi> (which is no other thing but fixed Salt of Tartar diſſolved in ſome Flegm) did ferment with the Spirits of Salt, Vitriol, <note place="margin">Pag. 97.</note> Sulphur and Niter, and did precipitate, after the Fermentation, ſome
<pb n="160" facs="tcp:47737:91"/>Matter from thoſe Bodies: Oil of Tartar is therefore an Alka<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>li, ſince it ferments with Acid Spirits; for, as you grant, there is none but Alkali's which can ferment with Acids; and, it is falſe that you aſſure us, That this Oil is Acid; for, if it was Acid, it would ferment with Alkali's, and never with Acids, the which is contrary to what we ſee. <note place="margin">Pag. 98, 99, 100.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p>The Reaſon which you ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of the Efferveſcence which happens in the Diſſolution of Metals in Aqua fort. is a Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject as little ſatisfactory: for, you ſay, That it is not the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qua fort. that cauſes this Diſſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution and Efferveſcence, but rather a volatile ſulphurous Spirit which animates the Aqua
<pb n="161" facs="tcp:47737:91"/>Fort. to the Diſſolution of the Mettal, ſince that being eva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porated, or ſeparated there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>from by the Acid of Salt of Tartar, the reſt of the Water acts no more; for, aſſuredly (continue you) it is this im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfect, or to ſpeak more pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly, embrionated Sulphur which ſymbolizeth with the Sulphur of a Mettal, and more or leſs with one than with an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other, whence come the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſity of Aqua fortis; and, that one acts upon one Mettal and not upon another, &amp;c. This Sulphur is impatient for a uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on with a Sulphur more per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect than it ſelf, therefore it ſearches through the Mercury, and ſtriving to be united with it <hi>per minima,</hi> it divides it, &amp;c.</p>
                  <pb n="162" facs="tcp:47737:92"/>
                  <p>Experience fully deſtroyes the appearances of this Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoning; for, it is moſt certain, That Acids, as Spirit of Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, diſſolves imperfect Metals, which have more Mercury than Sulphur, as Silver, Lead, &amp;c. and, as for Gold which hath a great deal more Sulphur than Mercury, it cannot be diſſolv'd but in ſalt Menſtruums, as Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of Sea-ſalt. I have explai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned all theſe different Effects ſo clearly, in the preceeding Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſes of this Book, That the repetition thereof would be both uſeleſs and troubleſom: And, as to the Hindrance that Oil of Tartar brings to thoſe Diſſolutions which you attri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute to its Acidity, it is not at all probable; ſince I have for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly
<pb n="163" facs="tcp:47737:92"/>ſhewn, That it was an Alkali: and the true Reaſon of it is, That the Oil of Tartar being a powerful Alkali, ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſorbs the Acids which held the Metals in Diſſolution, and the Metals being no longer a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gitated or ſtir'd by their points are precipitated into a powder, to the bottom of the Veſſel.</p>
                  <p>Truly, I ſee as little Juſtice in your Definition of Alkali; You argue it to be a thing made Salt by Cremation, <note place="margin">Pag. 102.</note> as though it was not a Salt before: and, this Definition doth in no wiſe ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain the Nature of Alkali, but only agrees with fixed Alkali: yet it is certain, that ſome are Volatile, which are elevated &amp; ſublimed with the leaſt Heat, as your ſelf acknowledgeth, <note place="margin">p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>. 94.95.</note> where
<pb n="164" facs="tcp:47737:93"/>you ſpeak of Tartar: You ſay, It retains the volatile Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kali of Wine, which cauſeth it to break the Veſſels by its com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bating with the Acidity of the Tartar, when it is diſtilled a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone by Retort, The Recipient being very exactly luted, &amp; the fire too much preſt. But I have moreover ſufficiently formerly proved, That Alkali as well as Acid was actually in all Bodies; and, that to be Alkali, it is not neceſſary, that a Body be made ſalt by Cremation. Moreover, the Doctrine which you pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mote contradicts it ſelf; <note place="margin">Pag 104, 105.</note> for, if the Alkali was no other, as you would have it, than only the Sulphur of the Mixt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained in a portion of water un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the form of Salt by the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition
<pb n="165" facs="tcp:47737:93"/>poſition of the fire, it would moſt eaſily be deſtroy'd, and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently as Volatile as you pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend it fix'd.</p>
                  <p>That which you ſay of the Liquor Alkaheſt of Helmont, and the Doves of the Diana of Philalethes, appears to me ſo frivolous, That I think it not worth my ſtay to refute it, no more than ſeveral other Paſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges of your Letter. It ſufficieth me to make you know the prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipal Points wherein you have deviated from Experience and Reaſon: and alſo to make you take Notice, That it is much more honorable to keep Silence than to employ your Time and Pen unjuſtly to cenſure the Works of others, and to rage
<pb n="166" facs="tcp:47737:94"/>and rail without Reaſon, or any ſeeming Truth, againſt a Facul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty whoſe Credit and Reputati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on you are in Juſtice obliged to vindicate.</p>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="half_title">
                  <pb facs="tcp:47737:94" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <p>Errores PHLEBOMIAE DETECTI.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:47737:95"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:47737:95"/>
                  <p>Errores PHLEBOMIAE DETECTI.</p>
                  <p>Or, The ERRORS OF PHLEBOTOMY DISCOVERED, For the USE of Tyro's:</p>
                  <p>By <hi>J. W. </hi>
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>Thomas Dawks.</hi> 1689.</p>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="essay">
                  <pb facs="tcp:47737:96"/>
                  <pb n="1" facs="tcp:47737:96"/>
                  <head>
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>. Sive Errores PHLEBOTOMIAE detecti.</head>
                  <p>THAT Phlebotomy ſhould be with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out its Errors is ſtrange, ſince all humane Operations are ſubject to Miſtakes; for, <hi>Humanum est er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rare:</hi> but, That theſe Errors ſhould be maintained with ſo much Stifneſs, when Reaſon and Experience daily demonſtrates them to be contrary to the ſafeſt way of Healing, is moſt ſtrange! becauſe, ſuch Perſons muſt needs either obſtinately de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſe the Dictates of Reaſon, and go on in their old Dangerous roads, meerly for want of knowing better, or to excuſe themſelves
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:47737:97"/>from thoſe more troubleſom tho' ſafer wayes: Or elſe ſuch perſons ſhew them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves Uncapable to be taught by Reaſon or Experiments, by paying too great a Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>o ſome few Opinions of our an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Phyſicians, as well as to the Male-pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice of our European Neighbours.</p>
                  <p>Methinks, where the Lives of our miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable fellow Brethren are ſo nearly concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, we might be the leſs raſh and incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderate in our Practice, eſpecially, if we are not ſo horridly wicked as to be void of all Thoughts of a Future State, wherein we ſhall either receive the juſt Merrit of our unchriſtian Actions in endleſs Torments; or, the gracious reward of our charitable and juſt Endeavours in eternal Enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments</p>
                  <p>And, That Phlebotomy, as it is now raſhly and careleſsly uſed, may appear to be in many Caſes, dangerouſly and cruelly infl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>cted upon Mankind by unthinking and partial Phyſicians: Give me leave to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent you with theſe following Reaſons to prove it.</p>
                  <pb n="7" facs="tcp:47737:97"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>First,</hi> The Blood is by all granted to be the Vehicle of Life, and that whereby Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture performs all her Operations: and, as the Blood is an Inſtrument of Nature, ſo it is a Product of Nature, which is proved by comparing Childhood and Maturity to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether; a Child hath not ſo much Blood as a man; therefore it is neceſſary it ſhould have its generation and augmentation, which can only be by what it had a begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning from.</p>
                  <p>Nature alſo doth not generate or aug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment the Quantity of the Blood in vain, and this is apparent, becauſe all Philoſophy maintains, She doth none of her Works in vain, but for the end of Health and conſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation thereof. Now, it follows, That the Diminution of that which Nature hath or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained for Conſervation, muſt produce a Chaſm in the matter to be conſerved: this may be proved in any continued Matter, whether Lines, Superficies or Solids, for, the matter conjoined being diſſolved the Matters conjoined are ſeparated. Now, a Chaſm cannot be made without Loſs of ſome Intention of Nature, if it could, it
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:47737:98"/>would neceſſarily follow, That the thing making the Chaſm was made in vain, which is notoriouſly againſt the Principles of Philoſophy: and, a Loſs of any of the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentions of Nature, is in order only to her Diſſolution, becauſe it obſtructs Nature in her Conſtructive and Conſervative Ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations; and a Diſſolution of Nature will produce a Deſtruction of the humane Frame.</p>
                  <p>And, it muſt needs be ſo becauſe Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture her ſelf, being Conſervatrix, is taken away. In Nature lies the band of Union by which all Particles and Parts of the Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy are knit and joined together, and this Band is only in the Medium of Life; for, there is no Difference between the Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um of Union and the things to be united; This Medium is the Blood, and the things to be united are the humane Frame and Life: Indeed, it is the Life it ſelf that is the Real uniting Principle, which becauſe it is immaterial and ſo without Parts, and not capable of Diviſion of it ſelf, ſo it is impoſſible to be diſunited from any thing it is joined, unleſs the Medium of that Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>junction
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:47737:98"/>be firſt deſtroyed which is firſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gun by a Chaſm; and, as a Chaſm is the Medium of the Separation of united things, ſo the Diminution of the Medium of union is a Diminution of the United Forces, and conſequently an Inlet to the Deſtruction of the ad<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>j<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ined Principles: for, the Medium, of Uni<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ion adds ſtrength to the things united by Virtue of their Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>junction or being made one; for, <hi>Vis unita fortior;</hi> hence it is evident, That the Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraction of that Medium muſt be the Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution of that Strength, and proportion<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able as that Medium is augmented or di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſhed, ſo muſt the Strength of the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joined things either increaſe or decreaſe: and, I have before proved, Nature doth nothing in vain.</p>
                  <p>From all which it follows,</p>
                  <p>That the taking away of the Blood, <hi>Firſt,</hi> Hinders Nature in performing her Opera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions. <hi>Secondly,</hi> Diminiſheth her Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration. <hi>Thirdly,</hi> Fruſtrates her Intention. <hi>Fourthly,</hi> Diminiſheth the Medium of Unition. <hi>Fifthly,</hi> Impares the Strength.
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:47737:99"/>
                     <hi>Sixtly,</hi> Opens a Caſm, which being ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently wide lets our Life, and introduceth Death. Wherefore ſince a diminution of the Quantity of the Blood cannot be done without manifeſt Dammage, the Alteration of the Quality, when it is hurt, ought to be attempted ſome ſafer way.</p>
                  <p>And, whereas it is generally believed, That Blood-letting often prevents a Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, yet if we examine the thing more ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curately, we ſhall rather find, That it makes us obnoxious to a Fever. It is the Opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of that great and learned Champion for Blood letting, Dr. <hi>Willis,</hi> in his Book of Fevers, <hi>pag.</hi> 75. <hi>Prae coeteris vero obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vatione constat quod Crebra ſanguinis miſſio homines febri aptiores reddat:</hi> and again, he ſaies, <hi>Hinc fit ut qui Crebra mittunt ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guinem, non tantum in febres ſunt procli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ves, verum etiam pingueſcere ſoleant prop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter cruorem ſucco ſulphureo plus impregna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum.</hi> But whether this ſulphurous Juice is the true Cauſe of either, I ſhall not at preſent examine: ſince it is alſo the Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of divers learned Phyſicians, That Blood-letting, by cooling the Body in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priving
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:47737:99"/>it of its vital Spirits, does ſo qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lify it, as it cannot caſt out that dewy ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crementitious ſubſtance which ſweats through the Tunicles of the Veins (which is the Matter of Fault) by Perſpiration, but ſuffers it to congeal under the skin in that thick pingueons Subſtance called Fat: hence Peſons that are coldly conſtituted are fat without Phlebotomy: and hence al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo it is, That fat perſons are the ſmalleſt Eaters, by reaſon of the lack of internal Heat. But a little after the Doctor ſpeaks yet more fully to the Purpoſe, <hi>Qui ſangui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem habent ſale volatilizato bene ſutura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>i ſunt minus Febribus obnoxii: hinc etiam qui ſaepius ſanguinem emittunt ad Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bres aptiore ſunt.</hi> Thus far he whoſe ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gle Teſtimony in ſufficient.</p>
                  <p>And, ſince it appears, That it doth ſo little hinder the approach of a Feaver that it rather furthers it, it ſeems impoſſible That it ſhould abſolutely and alone cure any Fever. For, it is granted by all Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſicians, That a Fever has a property to pol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute the Blood, and, that this can be taken away <hi>à posteriori,</hi> that is, by withdrawing
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:47737:100"/>what is putrified and contaminated, ſeems very abſurd to think, being contrary to that Philoſophick Axiom, <hi>Manente cauſa, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>net Effectus.</hi> Beſides, It is generally be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved, That the material cauſe of a Fever do's not poſſeſs the Veſſels about the heart, but rather the <hi>Vena cava:</hi> and therefore how can Blood-letting be ſuppoſed to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>move either, the efficient or material cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes thereof? Wherefore conſequently, it can be no true Remover of a Fever, but only an Abater of one of its moſt trouble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſem Symptoms, <hi>viz.</hi> Heat: which it do's by impoveriſhing the Stock of vital Spirits, which maitaining Conteſt with the Radix of the Fever, does by that contentious Moti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on cauſe that preternatural exceſſive Heat and Ebulition of the Blood, which is parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cularly affected therewith: hence it is, That old Perſons, whoſe vital Spirits are poor in quantity, and conſequently not able to combate ſo ſtrongly with the Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſe, do not appear ſo hot in a Fever as thoſe whoſe Spirits are ſtronger, and in a larger quantity: and other perſons after a tedious Warfare with this cruel Diſeaſe,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:47737:100"/>ſome ſmall time before Death, the Spirits having given up the Victory, as not being able any longer to oppoſe the ſame, do ſeem to be totally freed from all the Sym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptoms of their Fever: For, as I ſaid, the Spirits by reaſon of their Paucity and Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>becility do then reſign up their noble Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers to the Mercy of the Diſeaſe, whoſe, truculent Forces quickly invades the very Royal Pavillion of Life it ſelf, and as ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denly ſubverts it, by committing it into the frozen Arms of a drowzy Death.</p>
                  <p>Whence it is held as a dangerous Prog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noſtick when a Fever abates in the Violen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy of its Symptoms, without any CRISIS or natural Aſſiſtance, or without any me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicinal Aid, or without any certain Signs of approaching Health, as well as ſure To<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kens of Nature's obtaining the Victory over the Diſeaſe.</p>
                  <p>So that it is no Wonder why Phlebotomy ſeems to afford ſo great Refreſhment to the afflicted, even in the moſt troubleſom Symptoms; becauſe, by depriving Nature
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:47737:101"/>of ſome of her provoked Forces, it com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pells the reſt for want of Power to ſuffer patiently the Cruelty of the Diſeaſe, which if it be not very malignant, as thoſe Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers called <hi>Ephemera, Synochus non putri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>da,</hi> and ſometimes in thoſe putrid ones called, <hi>Synochus putrida,</hi> and the continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al <hi>Quotidian, Tertian</hi> and <hi>Quartan,</hi> the Contention ceaſing, and the corrupted blood being partly let out, and the reſt (by ſome proper Medicament) being corrected and amended, Nature doth with much Difficul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and with great Debility at length obtain a pleaſing Health.</p>
                  <p>Now, if Phlebotomy did only let out the corrupted Blood, and left ſtill behind thoſe Spirits which uſed to flow with it, then Blood-letting, by partly removing the Effect, might eaſe Nature of a great deal of that, which ſhe otherwiſe muſt with a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundance more Toil caſt out: And, Reaſon would tell us, That the natural Forces be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſtill the ſame in Quantity and Power, and the Inimical vitiated Blood being di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſhed and partly let out, Nature muſt
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:47737:101"/>needs be the better able to caſt out and purge the reſt. But, ſince we find that the Blood and Spirits are Correlatives, and do iſſue out together, the Spirits going forth in ſuch Quantity, and the Blood let forth could be Vehicle too. This proves then That Phlebotomy as it doth take away ſome of the corrupted Blood, ſo it takes away alſo thoſe Spirits which might have aſſiſted to its correction ſome better way: thereby rather weakning than aſſiſting Nature.</p>
                  <p>But Phlebotomy being uſed in any ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lignant Diſeaſe is utterly deſtructive with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a Miracle: for, in the Meazles, Small Pox, Plague, &amp;c. It moſt commonly ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructs Nature in her Intentions, ſo much debilitating her ſtrength, that ſhe oft proves unable to caſt forth the malignant Matter, but by its poiſon is wholly over-come and deſtroy'd, or, at leaſt is not capable of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king an exact Purgation; and though with extream hazard, ſhe eſcape Death, yet there is ſuch a ſtock of malignant matter left behind ſecretly lurking in the Maſs of Blood which will, upon a ſmall Excitation,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:47737:102"/>diſcover its preſence there by untoward troubleſom Symptoms, unleſs by powerful Remedies it be diſpoſſeſt before it has fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented it ſelf to that height.</p>
                  <p>It has been the Audacity of ſome Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſicians to preſcribe Blood-letting even in the Small Pox and Plague, ſuppoſing That in the firſt, the corrupted Blood being part<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly let out, it would be impoſſible that the afflicted perſons ſhould have ſo many of thoſe deforming Pusſles, as they other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe would have had, and therefore Blood-letting in ſuch Caſes might be law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, if it were upon no other account but the preſerving the threatned Beauty of a youthful Face. 'Tis true by allaying the Efferveſcence of the Blood, and weakning the expulſive Faculty, partly, as they ſay, by reaſon part of that Corruption is let forth, which otherwiſe, perhaps, might have made ſome hundreds of thoſe filthy Pusſles: There is, (if the Diſeaſed eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cape Death) a great diminution of them, and thereby thoſe ſweet Features which they before poſſeſt are not wholy raſed.
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:47737:102"/>But that this cannot be performed without <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>nifeſt Hazard of the Patient's Life, Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience and Reaſon hath ſhewen, ſince ſo many great Perſons have fell meerly to ſave a handſome Face. The Spirits by Blood-letting being diminiſhed and ener<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vated, ſo that they can no longer endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour for their own Recovery: for, as <hi>Hippocrates</hi> ſaith, <hi>Natura est morborum Medi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>,</hi> Beſides, Phlebotomy gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally, by weakning the retentive Faculty, produces a Diarrhaea, which was ever ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted a dangerous Symptom in malig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap> Diſeaſes, but moſt particularly in the Small Pox: and, upon this Account it is That Phlebotomy ſometimes by producing <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> accident, on the a ſimple Feaver.</p>
                  <p>But, in the Plague, they pretend That the opening of a Vein is neceſſary for Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vention ſake, Be<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>auſe the leſs Efferveſcence is in the Circulation of the Blood, the leſs obnoxious we are to the Contagion. The moſt noted man of this Opinion, I find to be the above mentioned Dr. <hi>Willis,</hi> in his Book of Fevers, pag. <hi>157.</hi> Where he ſaies,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:47737:103"/>
                     <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>bi adest Plethora cum magna ſanguinis Turgeſcentia, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ut quibus longa Conſuetudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne ſanguis ſolenniter mitti ſolebat iis ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nam ſecare convenit, quo enim ſanguis mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus efferveſcet &amp; ſine tumultu in vaſis cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culatur <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>o tardius Lue pestifera Contami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natur.</hi> A moſt injurious Opinion, ſince by weakning the Spirits, ſhe becomes the leſs able to withſtand ſo lethal an Enemy: For, if a Plenitude be the Pretence: by a more ſpare Dyet, and other proper things, it may be made ſo harmleſs as not in the leaſt to aſſiſt that poyſonous Diſeaſe, when it has ſeized us, nor to incourage it in any way to ſeize upon us.</p>
                  <p>Wherefore to go and let any infected perſon Blood, is a ſhort Way to Cure them of the Diſeaſe, and Rid them of their Lives together: ſince it ſo waſtfully ſpends the vital Powers, by whom only this cruel Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſe can be withſtood and vanquiſhed. For, if Nature, at any time has ſo far prevail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with the Diſeaſe, as to collect the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt part of the malignant Matter into one place, and does endeavour to caſt it forth
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:47737:103"/>in Botches, Boils, or Carbuncles: which commonly appear in the Emunctories: whoſe Gland<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>es are then tumified with this poyſonous Humour: Blood-letting being then admitted, Nature dos not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly for want of Power ceaſe to proſecute her deſign, but this vicious Humour is remitted <hi>ob fugam vacui:</hi> and ſo quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſpreads it ſelf through the whole Maſs of Blood, aſſiſting thoſe poiſonous Parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles (which were there before, and which Nature was obſtructed, by Phlebotomy, from purging out) to the deſtruction of the miſerable Patient.</p>
                  <p>It is for the very ſame Cauſe that thoſe common Breakings out of the Body, in large Swelling, in the Emunctories, and in ſmall Pimples and Scurfs, all over the Body do all diſappear after a plentiful Emiſſion of Blood: The vitiated Matter being returned to ſupply the Deficiency of the Blood newly let out: and, it is there ſo long circulated 'till it is thence caſt out by Perſpiration: or elſe, if it be very venemouns, it infects the whole Maſs: ſo
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:47737:104"/>that, perhaps, an accute and dangerous Diſeaſe ſucceeds it, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> it be neither very Malignant, and Yet the whole Maſs be contaminated, thoſe Pimples, Bliſters and Scurff keep ſo long in and lurk ſecret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in the <hi>B</hi>lood: either 'till Nature has recruited her Forces, and be ins to caſt them out again, in order to the freeing herſelf from thoſe noxious Particles (tho' perhaps it be impoſſible for her alone and unaſſiſted to perform it, yet ſhe alwayes endeavours her own Redemption if ſhe be not obſtructed) of elſe, 'till thoſe Vene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous Corpuſcles are by ſome accidental Cauſe excited to fermentation, whereby they pollute the <hi>B</hi>lood to a greater degree; ſo that the whole Fleſh is ſo depraved as to appear in a Meaſly Scurfy and filthy form, and may, perhaps, at laſt merrit the name of Incurable Leproſy.</p>
                  <p>It is the Opinion of ſome Phyſicians, That <hi>B</hi>lood-letting is very proper, yea, Neceſſary in the Scurvy; among whom <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> find the often, quoted Doctor <hi>Willis</hi> t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> be one, who ſaies, in the <hi>B</hi>ook of the Scur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vy,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:47737:104"/>pag. 256. <hi>Cum enim Liquor ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guineous valde impurus evaſit nullo Remediorum genere certius emendatur, quam crebra &amp; parva extramiſſione, quippe ſanguini veteri corrupto quoti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es educitur recens melior &amp; defoecatior Existit.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Now, thererefore it is granted by Moſt, That the <hi>B</hi>lood is better in ſome venal Pipes than in others, which may eaſily be proved by any who ever ſaw many rob'd of this rubid Liquor: for, In ſome it ſpouts out <hi>B</hi>ad at firſt, and better afterwards: in others, The quite contrary: Wherefore, if this be true, as it moſt certain and undeniable, Then the Queſtion is, How ſhall we know when that vitiated parcel of <hi>B</hi>lood, which we ſo much ſeek to remove, has taken up its abode in the inferiour parts of the Veins of the Arm, and in the Arteries tending thereto, that we may let it out: For if it be not there, it is impoſſible we ſhould extract it: ſince all the other Arteries are too re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mote:
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:47737:105"/>and, ſo in ſtead of the Bad, we may take away the Good: and, beſides if we did take away ſome of the Bad, for its impoſſible to take all, yet it may be queſtioned, Whether the new made Blood may not be vitiated in its Preparation, before it comes to be circulated with the old, as undoubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edly it is, both in the Liver, Spleen and other Viſcera's: Wherefore, tho' a new Maſs of Blood may well be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected this way, yet not without a cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>el wracking of Nature, in forcing her to labour ſo hard for Life, being be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore tormented by ſo ſtubborn a Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſe: yet we cannot expect to have it much better than the former, but rather worſe, unleſs we uſe ſome pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per Remedies to cut off the Cauſes, and to purify it in the Fountain; the which Remedies would as well have corrected and amended the Old Maſs of Blood as this New one, ſince no Blood in a curable Diſeaſe can be ſo corrupted, but it may be reduced to its priſtin Sanity without extramiſſion of
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:47737:105"/>any part of it: which proves, That its not a Real Corruption, but a Diſpoſition thereto: for, an abſolute Corruption is a total Deſtruction of its firſt Eſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial Form, and the Aſſumption of a new one, which by no means will ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit of being reformed into its priſtine one, according to that Philoſophical Axiom, <hi>A privatione ad habitum non datur Regreſſus.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Yet we finde, That the Blood, tho it ſeem to be deeply corrupted, may ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſily with proper and efficacious Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caments be reſtored to its former Soundneſs and Pureneſs, becauſe it has not totally loſt that Form with which it was firſt ſtam'd.</p>
                  <p>But, yet further, Suppoſe the Scor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>butick Malignity did lodg no where but in the Blood [which is indeed falſe] yet new Blood coming to be circulated with that old which was leſt, would by meer contact be, in a ſmall time, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qually affected by thoſe noxious Parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles, as that: Such a fermentative
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:47737:106"/>Force has the Seminal <hi>Ens</hi> of a Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſe, as it can quickly multiply it ſelf to a Wonder, if it be not reſtrained or cut off. Wherefore Blood-letting in theſe Caſes does not appear, being Examined by Reaſon and Experience, to be ſo very Neceſſary, as ſome would make us believe it is.</p>
                  <p>Therefore to make an End of all, it appears, That the Means uſed to let out bad Blood, without removing the Efficient Cauſe thereof, is no direct Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod of Healing.</p>
                  <p>Now, Phlebotomy lets out bad Blood without removing the Efficient Cauſe thereof; <hi>Ergo,</hi> Phlebotomy is no direct Method of Healing.</p>
                  <p>The <hi>Major</hi> is eaſily proved, For whatſoever ſuffers the Cauſe to remain can never totally remove the Effect: Now, Phlebotomy ſuffers the Cauſe to remain, therefore it can never abſolute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly remove the Effect.</p>
                  <pb n="25" facs="tcp:47737:106"/>
                  <p>The <hi>Minor</hi> is alſo as eaſily proved; For, if the Cauſe of bad Blood were cut off, the Fever and Scurvy depend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thereon would quickly ceaſe; the which we find rarely to happen, ſince after a frequent Extraction of Blood, we find the Fever and moſt of the Sym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptoms ſtill remain, and the Diſeaſe grows more ſtrong, even to a total de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>privation of all the vital Faculties, of their Power and Vitallity.</p>
                  <p>I own Blood Letting may do leaſt Harm, yea be very Beneficial, by ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cident, in ſome Reſpects, in ſome few Diſeaſes; of which the moſt noted are, a Frenzy, Quinſy, Pleuriſy, an inve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terate and ſtubborn Head-ach, and in ſome Fevers, which be in no wiſe malig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant; as alſo in Contuſions, Rheuma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſms and Intermitting Fevers, but it muſt be in young and ſtrong Bodies, if it be done without any cauſe of Fear; and in ſome few other Diſeaſes: But eſpecially, it is moſt proper to temper the plethorick Bodies of our age, who
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:47737:107"/>by an extravigant Deſtruction of vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Liquors cauſe themſelves to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bound in that pretious balſamick vital Liquor.</p>
                  <p>It helps a Frenzy by abating the Ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferveſcence of the Blood, in diminiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Vital Spirits.</p>
                  <p>It helps a Quinzy by Revulſion and drawing back the Blood into the Veins which would have putrified there, that it may ſupply the loſs of that which was let out.</p>
                  <p>In a Pleuriſy, it obſtructs alſo the Apoſtumation of the Blood collected in the <hi>Pleura</hi> and Intercoſtal Branches of the <hi>Aorta</hi> by Revulſion, for that Blood there ready to putrify, by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of the great heat of the Parts, and its own Diſpoſition to Putrefaction does, as the Blood is drawn out of the Arm, repaſs into the Superiour Arteries, and ſo becomes again circulated in them: the Abſceſs thereof being thereby pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vented.</p>
                  <pb n="27" facs="tcp:47737:107"/>
                  <p>It cures an inveterate Head-Ach by reaſon it appeaſes the Fury of the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits there, and by reaſon it depleats the Veins and Arteries, wherefore 'tis, they are not ſo diſtended and pained as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore.</p>
                  <p>And, as for Fevers, I have told you already how it comes to be aſſiſting to their Cure, only intermitting Feavers ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cidentally are cur'd by altering the Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation, and by putting Nature into a Fear of Death, wherefore ſhe muſters up all her Forces to oppoſe it, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by very often the Root of the Fever is in this great Hurry and Commotion cut off and expell<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> for, as <hi>Dureti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us</hi> ſaith, <hi>Animi act ones incidente ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qua occaſione fortius agunt preſertim in morturis:</hi> Whence alſo in Swoonings and Aopoplectick fits it proves benefi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial: and, hence alſo it is, That great Fears have often been a means, by ſtir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring up all the natural Forces for their own Safety, to rid ſome Perſons of chro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nick accute and almoſt incurable Diſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:47737:108"/>as Experience has often manife<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted.</p>
                  <p>Rheumatiſms it cures by Derivation; and ſo it doth ſom Coughs, by cauſing the ſharp Lympha which Tickles the Lungs by its ſharp pointed Corpuſcles; the which alſo afflict the Nerves and Ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dons with accute Pains to be diſcharg'd from thence mediately into the ſubcla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vian Veins, to ſupply the loſs of the Blood let out, and into the Meſenterial Glandula's, to be mixed with the Chyle; alſo to promote the ſpeedy making the like quantity of Blood: hence ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times doth the Cauſe of a greedy Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petite proceed afte<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>B</hi>lood-letting, and after the retreat of a ſharp Diſeaſe: for Nature being ſtudious to repair her loſs, and eſpecially When ſhe has not been too much weakned by the Diſeaſe or <hi>B</hi>lood-letting, do's manifeſt her wants by theſe hungry Symptoms: It ſeems to aſſiſt the Circulation of the <hi>B</hi>lood, when it is congealed by reaſon of the Obſtruction of its Circulation in
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:47737:108"/>the ſmall Veins, which by the Contuſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on are ſo ſqueezed that they wholly deny its flux, becauſe it ſeems to afford it more Room for that Circulation: but if we conſider, That the Blood is Conglebated only, as I ſaid, in the ſmalleſt Veins, and that the thinneſt and moſt fluid Blood ſpins out at the Orifice: we cannot think it can much further its quiet Circulation, ſince fluidity is the greateſt Promoter of it.</p>
                  <p>Laſtly, By its waſting the Spirits and depriving us of that pure nutritive Juice the Blood, it keeps us back, not ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring Nature to ſtore up ſo much Nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triment to her ſelf, and thereby renders us equally as needy as if we put a greater reſtraint upon our Appetites and indulged them far leſs than we do.</p>
                  <p>To the former Advantages by Phle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>botomy, here is added, by another hand, this further Benefit, <hi>viz.</hi> That it is of excellent uſe for Women, whe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> their
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:47737:109"/>Terms dodg with them, and begin to leave them; and to prevent the ſettling of them in their Limbs, or in their own Veſſels putrifying and cauſing Ulcers, Sores, Piles and Fiſtula's in the inferi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our Parts, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> to prevent all which Evils, Women ſo affected ought to bleed once a month for 3 Months together.</p>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               </div>
            </body>
            <back>
               <div type="erratum">
                  <p>Errores Phlebot. p. 10. l. 18 <hi>Crebrò.</hi> p. 11. l. 5. <hi>Fat.</hi> p. 12. l. 6. <hi>above.</hi> p. 15. l. 5. <hi>as the.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="publishers_advertisement">
                  <pb facs="tcp:47737:109"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:47737:110"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:47737:110"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>Advertiſement.</hi> All Dr. <hi>Salmon's</hi> Works are certainly to be ſold by <hi>Tho. Dawks</hi> living on Addle hill in Carter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lane near <hi>S.</hi> Paul's Church-yard. Alſo the ſaid Doctor's Medicines truly pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared, are in his abſence to be ſold by his Wife, at his Houſe, at the Blew Balcony, by the Ditch-ſide near Hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>born Bridge.</head>
                  <p>There is alſo preparing for the ſaid <hi>Dawks</hi>'s Preſs, A Practical Diſcourſe concerning <hi>Swearing;</hi> Not only-ſharp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly reprooving the vain, falſe, raſh, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſiderate Swearer; but alſo chiefly reprimanding the Over-wiſe <hi>Quaker,</hi> in the midst of all his vain-glorious Shew of <hi>ſeeming Holineſs,</hi> proving that he moſt abominably abuſeth all thoſe Scriptures he brings for Refuſing to take an Oath before Authority, when the Law of God commands it, and the Glory of God as well as the Neceſſity of his Neighbour require it, &amp;c.</p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:47737:111" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <p>Place this leaf laſt of all.</p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:47737:111" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               </div>
            </back>
         </text>
      </group>
   </text>
</TEI>
